<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The secrets of physick and philosophy divided into two bookes: in the first is shewed the true and perfect order to distill, or draw forth the oyles of all manner of gummes, spices, seedes, roots, and hearbs, with their perfect taste, smell and vertues. In the second is shewed the true and perfect order to prepare, calcine, sublime, and dissolue all manner of minerals, and how ye shall draw forth their oyles and salts, which are most wonderfull in their operations, for the health of mans bodie. First written in the German tongue by the most learned Theophrastus Paraselsus, and now published in the English tongue, by Iohn Hester, practitioner in the art of distillation.</title>
            <title>True and perfect order to distill oyles out of al maner of spices.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 119 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08906</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19182</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113991</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849219</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849219</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14357</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08906)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14357)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 998:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The secrets of physick and philosophy divided into two bookes: in the first is shewed the true and perfect order to distill, or draw forth the oyles of all manner of gummes, spices, seedes, roots, and hearbs, with their perfect taste, smell and vertues. In the second is shewed the true and perfect order to prepare, calcine, sublime, and dissolue all manner of minerals, and how ye shall draw forth their oyles and salts, which are most wonderfull in their operations, for the health of mans bodie. First written in the German tongue by the most learned Theophrastus Paraselsus, and now published in the English tongue, by Iohn Hester, practitioner in the art of distillation.</title>
                  <title>True and perfect order to distill oyles out of al maner of spices.</title>
                  <author>Paracelsus, 1493-1541, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Hermanni, Philippus. Constich distillierboeck.</author>
                  <author>Hester, John, d. 1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 196, [16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A[ugustine] M[athewes] for William Lugger, and are to bee sold at the Posterne Gate at Tower Hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Not in fact by Paracelsus.</note>
                  <note>An enlarged edition of: The true and perfect order to distill oyles out of al maner of spices.</note>
                  <note>"Secrets of phisicke and philosophie. The second booke ..", an adaptation of "Een constich distillierboeck" by Philippus Hermanni, has separate dated title page; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>With a final colophon leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Formulae, receipts, prescriptions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14357:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14357:1"/>
            <p>THE SECRETS OF PHYSICK and PHILOSOPHY, Divided into two Bookes:</p>
            <p>In the firſt is ſhewed the true and perfect order to diſtill, or draw forth the Oyles of all manner of Gummes, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Seedes, Roots, and Hearbs, with their perfect taſte, ſmell and vertues.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond is ſhewed the true and perfect order to prepare, calcine, ſublime, and diſſolue all manner of Minerals, and how ye ſhall dravv forth their oyles and Salts, which are moſt wonderfull in their Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, for the health of Mans Bodie.</p>
            <p>Firſt written in the German Tongue by the moſt learned <hi>Theophraſtus Paraſelſus,</hi> and <hi>now publiſhed in the Engliſh Tongue, by</hi> IOHN HESTER, Practitioner <hi>in the Art of Distillation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>William Lugger,</hi> and are bee ſold at the Poſterne Gate at Tower Hill. 1633.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14357:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14357:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Reverend Father in God, and his ſingular good Lord, <hi>Iohn Watſon,</hi> by the grace of God, Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter, and Prelate of</hi> the right Honourable Order <hi>of the Garter,</hi> I. H. <hi>wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth health and peace, and long life in</hi> IESVS CHRIST.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Rettie and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie is the tale (my Good Lord) that <hi>Plato</hi> tells in his <hi>Protago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14357:3"/>and ſomewhat appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to my preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and therefore not abſurd for mee to ſet downe, to the better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment of my pretence. Among other his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Inventions (as hee is in all his things moſt like himſelfe ſtill verie divine) hee ſheweth how <hi>Ioue</hi> looking down from heaven with a pitifull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard upon the hard &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition of men, ſeeing the ſundry calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and infinite miſeries that they were ſubject un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, while yet they lived ſavage like beaſts amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt
<pb facs="tcp:14357:3"/>beaſts, every man leading his life after the levell of his owne luſt, took order ſtrait with his winged Meſſenger <hi>Mercurie,</hi> to deſcend downe with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, with travell to collect and gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the diſperſed multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, that ſo united they might both bee ſtronger to defend themſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bruit beaſts their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemie: and linked as it were in a bodie po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique, each preſented as well with the dayly view of his owne want, as the continuall ſhew of the like lacke in others,
<pb facs="tcp:14357:4"/>might with ioynt aſſent and conſent (as driuen by neceſſitie) endevour to driue neceſſitie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. For the ſpeedier accompliſhing whereof, he had in charge to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh a law, that if any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them were found vnfurniſhed with iuſtice, and voyd of ſhamefaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: the ſame ſhould be compted as an vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table droane among la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring bees, and ſhould ſuffer puniſhment accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. A worthy talke, and fit ſo worthy a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher. By the which hee highly delivered in
<pb facs="tcp:14357:4"/>generall tearmes, that which wee dayly finde in particular proofe: to weet, no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, nor ſocietie to continue long happy where the members and parts ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of either for loue of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, or feare of ſhame are not like affectioned each other. Now leſt I ſhould ſeeme to allow of this tale in ſpeech, and to diſlike it in practice, I haue preſumed by this bare tranſlation, to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my forwardneſſe in furthering her that foſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers mee. And yet is not my Tranſlation ſo bare,
<pb facs="tcp:14357:5"/>(my good Lord) but that it carryeth in it more plainneſſe to the Reader, then perhaps they ſhall find in the firſt writer: For beſide that I haue culled out their choiſe things, I haue from the ſame choiſe proined, and cut off their ſuperfluitie, I haue ſupplied their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, I haue laid open their obſcuritie, and I haue ſhadowed their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults, neither yet arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating to my ſelfe, not derogating from them, but as <hi>Dies diem docet,</hi> So; <hi>Experimentum experiendo confirmatur.</hi> What my
<pb facs="tcp:14357:5"/>travel herein ſhal profit, I know not: but ſure I am, my trouble in the triall of them hath been great, my expences large, my proofes painfull, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all heerein plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſaue onely a little knowledge that I haue got, aboue the capacitie of the common ſort, a thing ſure that I value far aboue the price that it coſt me. Which know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge indeed ſuch is my groſſeneſſe, or ſuch the ſubtleneſſe of the matter if ſelfe that I can eaſilier by demonſtration ſhew it, then by declaration
<pb facs="tcp:14357:6"/>teach it: and therefore dare I not vnder-credite warrant perſpicuitie to all men, but to thoſe that are <hi>Filijartis,</hi> I promiſe more then I found, and yet found I more then they hauing would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly looſe: To the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue I may ſay, that as Hennes ſit, but hatch not Chickens in one day: ſo men reade, but learne not Artes in one day.</p>
            <p>To you, my good Lord, whoſe Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance heerein I craue for protection, whoſe iudgement and skill I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale
<pb facs="tcp:14357:6"/>to for favour, I muſt needs confeſſe they are not written) although loth to haue them maſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erleſſe like their maſter, I am over bold, to ſhroud them vnder your wings) to you I ſay they are not written, except overlade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the deepe and graue myſteries of higher and more heavenly Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, it may pleaſe you for delight, now &amp; then to looke downe into the plentifull and pleaſant ſtore-houſe of Nature; a matter no doubt that all your whole life time, you haue beene ſingular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:14357:7"/>delighted with, as moſt plainely do declare the ſingularitie, that you haue happily attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto in all &amp; every the parts of her, no leſſe to your great content at home, then to your like commendation abroad: which becauſe I can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther praiſe to your deſert not in praiſing pleaſe your deſire, I leaue to ſpeake farther of: onely deſiring your good Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with your wonted clemencie, to accept of this ſmall teſtimonie of my great good will, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring your ſelfe, that
<pb facs="tcp:14357:7"/>amongſt the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of your well wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, there is no one more dutifull then your poore</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Hester.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14357:8"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Xperience, the Daughter of Time, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of Travell, and the onely Iewell of a fewe the wiſer, is commonly, good Reader, ſet out at ſo high a price, &amp; valewed at ſo deare a pennyworth, that ſhee hath ever more Cheapners, then Chapmen, more lookers on her, then likers of her: and yet is ſhee bought of ſome, although one dramme of her coſt them a whole pound of Repentance. To deſcend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:14357:8"/>particulars, were but to tye thee to a weariſome tale, and to leade thee along tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe a tedious Labyrinth, ſtuffed full of Examples of former ages: a matter al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſo open to the view of the whole world, that for me to ſtirre further therein, were but to ſet a lighted can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in the bright Sunne. Onely for proofe, it may pleaſe thee (good Reader) to admit the Instance in my ſelfe. VVhen I began first to ſhake hands with the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of delights, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayed Youth are commonly carryed away with: and looking backe, (as it were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb facs="tcp:14357:9"/>my ſhoulder) ſaw the vaſt Sea of ſugered miſeries that I had waded through, I then beganne to thinke it high time to ſet downe a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Compaſſe to direct the remnant of the courſe that I haue yet to runne. And although at that time I car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in my purſe ſufficient wealth to ſupport my cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, in my bodie ſufficient health to maintaine my life; and thoſe both ſo reaſonable, as might haue ſatisfied a reaſonable man, (were not <hi>Natura hominum novi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis avida</hi>) yet found I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch content in the one, nor the other, as might lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb facs="tcp:14357:9"/>content mee to continue in that ſtate. But drawne on a while by this instinct, or infection (I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to callit) I was driven at laſt by a greedy kinde of jealouſie, to envie the ſtore that I ſaw in others, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of mine owne penurie: and therewithall I fell into conſideration how I might become one of the ſmal num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe, whom the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt number wondred at. To enter the ſtraight path that many the learned had happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their great commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion perfectly troden, I ſaw it almoſt unpoſsible, unleſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure I ſhould get mee
<pb facs="tcp:14357:10"/>where the Muſes dwell, to Oxford and Cambridge, and there putting my ſelfe Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice ſeven yeares to the ſeven liberall Scie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, might afterward become as long journeyman I cannot tell to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and in the end (as too many the learned doe) get I cannot tell what. This courſe yelded ſo courſe a liking, as I ſooner paſſed over it, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it: and caſting about a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with my ſelfe, I was combred with a hundred o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther odde crochets, all as farre beyond the compaſſe of my reach, as they were ſhort of the condition of my like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, till at lengh in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb facs="tcp:14357:10"/>of this muſe, <hi>I</hi> met in my mind with two ſuch mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, as in my conceit were the only Paragons of the reſt: the one gallant and gorgeous garniſhed with gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, bedect with jewels, ſole Ladie and Governeſſe of all the rich Mines and Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls that are in the bowels of the earth: the other ſweet &amp; odoriferous, adorn'd with flowers and hearbs, beautifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with delicate ſpices, ſole Lady and Regent of all plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant things that grow vpon the face of the earth. Theſe I vowed to ſerue and to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, euen to the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe of life and limme: neyther haue I
<pb facs="tcp:14357:11"/>greatly broken promiſe with them, though they haue not kept touch with me. Goodly and many golden mountains they promiſed me, Mary hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto haue ſeantly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med any leaden mole-hills. But howſoever the bargaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand between them and me, I am neither diſpoſed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them, nor excuſe my ſelfe. Wee agreed vpon wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and I weare their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries: their Cognuſance, ſuch as it is, I beare where I am not aſhamed to ſhew it: divers and ſundry their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres haue they imployed mee in, in the which I haue ſaithfully, painfully, and
<pb facs="tcp:14357:11"/>chargeably applied my ſelfe, and attained by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, (to mine owne deſtruction allmoſt) many their hidden ſecretes aſwell in Mettals and Mineralls, as in Hearbs and Spices: part wherof I haue diligently col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected together, and for non-payment of my board wages at their hands, am forced to ſet them with the reſidue of my skill to ſale, with offer vnto thee (good Reader) of preferment to the beſt things I have: yet at a farre eaſier price then they coſt me, being no leſſe my <hi>Summa ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum</hi> caſt vp, and the foot of my account ſet down,
<pb facs="tcp:14357:12"/>then the wasting out of my former health, and the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the little wealth I had. So that what experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ſoever I haue digged out of hard ſtones, blowne out from hot fire, raked out from foule aſhes, with great cost, and greater travaile, that haſt thou heere in my Booke to ſee, and in my ſhop to vſe with great eaſe at thy commandement.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Iohn Heſter.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14357:12"/>
                  <head>A TRVE AND perfect Order to make Oyles out of all maner of Gumms, Spice, Seeds, Roots and Hearbes Whereunto is added ſome of their vertues, gathered out of ſundrie Authors.</head>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake the pureſt Maſticke that may bee got, which is not mixed with Sandrake, or ſuch like, and beate it to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14357:13"/>powder, then put it into a glaſſe with a long neck, and put therein as much pure <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> as will cover it three fingers high, and then ſlop it cloſe that it take no ayre, then ſet it in warme horſe-dung, or in a ſoft Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neo, untill it bee diſſolved: then poure it into a glaſſe, and put therin as much wine as you ſhall thinke good, and diſtil it with a head, and receiver in ſand, with a ſmal fire, and you ſhall receiue both oyle and water toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the which you ſhall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate one from an other. Then increaſe your fire, and there will come fourth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other oyle, which ſmelleth ſomewhat of the fire, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> beſt to bee uſed outwardly.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14357:13"/>Yee may rectifie it againe with a ſmall fire, and ſo it will come ſweet.</p>
                     <p>The vertues of this oyle. It is excellent againſt all colde diſeaſes of the Maw: it comforeteth the liver and the lights, and all other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts of the body. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drunken it helpes thoſe that vomit or ſpit bloud: it conſumeth and breaketh all inward ſores. This oyle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing annoynted on the belly, it ſtoppeth the flixe, it ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth womens Termes, it is alſo good for the Mother that is fallen downe, if you annoynt it therewith, and the under part of the belly: It is good for young chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren whoſe Arſe-gut com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth forth, if you annoint
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14357:14"/>it therewith, and put it vp againe: It is alſo good for thoſe that are Burſten, if you annoynt them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and let them weare a Truſſe fit for that purpoſe: it helpeth freſh wounds ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry quickly, if you annoynt them therewith, and lay thereon a cloath wet in the ſame. It faſtneth the teeth if you annoynt the gummes therewith: it comforteth a weake ſtomack, and cauſeth good digeſtion, if you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynt it therewith.</p>
                     <p>This Oyle hath all the vertues of <hi>Masticke,</hi> but it is an hundred times more of force.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14357:14"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Mirra.</head>
                     <p>TAke pure Mirra that is new and fat, ſixe ounces, and put it into a glaſſe with a long necke, and put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on twelue ounces of pure rectified <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> then lute the glaſſe faſt, and ſet it in horſe-dung untill it bee diſſolved. Then poure it into an Vrinall with a head and a receiver, and diſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> in Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neo, with a ſoft fire, and the oyle will remaine in the bottome, the which ſtraine through a fine cloath, and keep it in a glaſſe. His ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are theſe.</p>
                     <p>This Oyle by his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Vertue preſerveth all
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14357:15"/>things fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> putrifaction that is annoynted therewith: likewiſe the face and hands being annointed therewith, it preſenteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſtate, a long time. It helpeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all ſtinking ſores and wounds quickly: it hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth: paines of the eares, if it be put therein. It preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the ſight of the Eyes, if your put one or two drops therein: Helpeth all paines of the Mother, if it be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed therewith: it ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the haire from falling: if any bee troubled with a Fever, let him annoint his whole-body therewith, and lay him downe to ſweate. This Oyle drieth and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth all Accidents after birth. Being drunke, it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14357:15"/>a ſweete breath, and helpeth the Cough: it is good againſt ſhort winde: it helpeth the ſtitch in the ſide; if you drinke thereof one dram: it ſtoppeth the flux of the bellys it maketh a cleane voyce. The Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits being annoynted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, it taketh away the ſtinch from thoſe parts: if yee mixe it with wine, and waſh the mouth therwith, it will comfort the gumm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>; and faſten the teeth: it is alſo good for wounds in the head.</p>
                     <p>If thou wilt uſe this oyle to preſerue any part, you ſhall uſe it in this order; firſt, make a Bath with ſome ſweet hearbs, and then hold that part the which you wil
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14357:16"/>preſerue over the fume, that the poares may open, then drie it with a linnen cloath, then annoynt it with this Oyle, and chafe it in: that being done, if there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine any yellowneſſe of the Oyle, ye may waſh it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with white wine. This Oyle would bee occupied when you are in the Stewe or hot-houſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Storax liquida.</head>
                     <p>TAke the pureſt Storax that you can get, and put it in a glaſſe with a long necke, and ſet it in horſe-dung for a moneth, then take it foorth, and diſtill it in an Vrinall that hath a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14357:16"/>wide mouth, in ſand, with a gentle fire, and you ſhall haue both Oyle and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the which you ſhall, ſeparate, and keepe to your vſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Riſius</hi> writeth in his great Booke of Diſtillations, that this Oyle hath the ſame Vertues that the Oyle of <hi>Mirra</hi> hath: but that it is a little more hot and pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Storax Calamite.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle may be made divers wayes, of the which I will ſhew you the beſt. Take the pureſt <hi>Storax</hi> that you can finde, and beat it into Powder, then put it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14357:17"/>into a long necked glaſſe, and put thereon pure recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> and lute the glaſſe, then ſet it in warme dung, or in a ſoft Balneo a moneth. Then diſtill it in ſand with a ſmall fire, and thou ſhalt haue both Oyle and water, which you ſhall ſeparate. You ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that towards the end of the diſtillation, there will aſcend a certaine matter like Manna, the which is pleaſant.</p>
                     <p>The vertues of this oyle. Three or foure droppes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drunke, it comforts the Breaſt and Lungs, and all inward parts: it helpes the paines of the Mother if it bee drunke, and alſo annoint thoſe parts therewith: it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14357:17"/>ſtoppes the Rheume that falles to the breaſt and neck: this being drunke, it makes a man merry, and of light courage, but beware you take not too much. If you put two or three drops into the Eares, it takes away the ſinging in them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin.</head>
                     <p>THis is made as you made the oyle of <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax Calamite,</hi> and is onely uſed in perfuming: ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtil this Benjamin with roſe water, but I thinke it will not bee ſo perfect in ſmell, nor ſo eaſily done.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:14357:18"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banum.</head>
                     <p>TAke the pureſt <hi>Galba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> thou canſt get, &amp; put it into a glaſſe cloſe luted, then ſet it in <hi>Balneo Mariae</hi> untill it bee diſſolved, then diſtill it with a ſoft fire, and then will come forth a faire yellow oyle, the which yee ſhall ſeparate.</p>
                     <p>This oyle being drunke, is good againſt an olde cough, and for ſuch as are ſhort winded, and can not eaſily draw their breath, but are alwayes panting &amp; brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. It is alſo very good for ſuch as are broken, and bruiſed within, and againſt Crampes, and ſhrinking of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14357:18"/>ſinewes. This oyle being drunke in Wine with oyle of Mirra, is good againſt all venome drunken, or ſhot into the bodie with vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous darts or arrowes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken in the ſame or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, it provoketh womens termes, and delivereth the dead childe. It hath the ſame vertue, if a perſume thereof bee received in the ſecret parts This Perfume doeth alſo helpe women that are grieved with the riſing, or ſtrangling of the Mother, and them that haue the Falling ſickneſſe, and being layd to the Navell, it cauſeth the Matrix or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is remooved from his naturall place, to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle againe. This oyle doth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14357:19"/>mollifie and ſoften, and draweth foorth thornes, ſplinters, or ſhivers, and cold humours, being mixed with any convenient vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent. It is good to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the ſide againſt the ſtopping and hardneſſe of the Milt. The perfume or ſent of this Oyle driveth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſerpents from the place where it is burned: and no venemous beaſts haue pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to hurt ſuch as be annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Oile of <hi>Galba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> and if ye mixe this oile with the root of <hi>Angelica,</hi> or the ſeed or root of <hi>Spon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilium,</hi> and touch any Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent or venemous beaſt therewith, it cauſeth them to die.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14357:19"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Sagapenum, a Gumme running out of the Herbe Ferula.</head>
                     <p>TAke this Gumme, and diſſolue it in ſtrong Wine, in <hi>Balneo Mariae,</hi> and then diſtill it in the ſand with a gentle fire.</p>
                     <p>This oyle is good for the ſtitch in the ſide, It taketh away the Cough that hath continued long : It helpeth the ſwelling of the breaſt, whereby the breaſt is ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. It is very good againſt the Crampe: it warmeth the joynts, and helpeth the paines of the hippes, and all ſuch like diſeaſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of cold. It is good for women that haue great pain in their-bed,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14357:20"/>if you annoynt the noſtrills therewith: For it driveth foorth both the quicke and the dead fruit quickly: being drunk with wine it helpeth againſt poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and is alſo good againſt the biting of an Adder: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put into the eye, it ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away ſpots: You ſhall note, that women with childe muſt take great heed of this Oyle.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make oile of Opoponax.</head>
                     <p>THis is made as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, and his vertues are theſe.</p>
                     <p>If you drinke three or foure droppes with Wine, it helpeth the Cough, and all impediments of the Milt:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14357:20"/>it helpeth alſo all Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Bladder, and cleanſeth it of all ſcabs and fores: It helpeth the ſtitch in the ſide: it cauſeth ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die deliverie in Women with childe: it helpeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt winde in the Matrix, and diſſolveth the hardneſſe of thoſe parts, and cauſeth the paine to ceaſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorbium.</head>
                     <p>THis it made as is ſayd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and his vertues are theſe.</p>
                     <p>Yee ſhall note, that this Oyle is not to bee occupy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed inwardly, by reaſon of his great heate, except it be mixed with ſome other
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14357:21"/>thing, as if it be mixed with honey, it purgeth the belly marveylouſly: it helpeth thoſe that are troubled with obliviouſneſſe, if yee annoynt the parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: It draweth foorth thornes and ſuch like out of the fleſh: it helpeth the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of an Adder: it is alſo good for ſtiffeneſſe of the joynts comming of cold, if ye annoynt the parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Ambre, or Succinum.</head>
                     <p>TAke <hi>Ambre,</hi> and beat it to powder, and put it into a glaſſe with a Head and a Receiver, and diſtill it in ſand with a gentle fire,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14357:21"/>and there will come foorth both oyle and water, the which ye ſhall ſeparate one from another.</p>
                     <p>This Oyle being perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtilled, is good againſt paines of the head, and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of ſinewes, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſwimming in the head, and falling ſickneſſe. If yee drinke thereof three or foure drops in the morning with <hi>Pionie</hi> water, it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth a man from all poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and peſtiferous ayres, if yee annoynt the noſtrilles therewith, or put it into ſome medicine fit for that purpoſe. It is excellent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt diſeaſes of the Blader and Reines, and driveth foorth the Stone, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voketh Vrine, if yee drinke
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14357:22"/>it with Malmeſie, or Parce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie water, or ſuch like. It helpeth the Collicke. and choking of the Matrix; if you alſo annoynt the parts therewith, it driveth foorth the fruit, and cauſeth a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to be fairely delivered; if ſhe drinke three or foure drops, it is good againſt all fluxes of the head.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niacum.</head>
                     <p>TAke this Gumme, and put it into a glaſſe cloſe luted: and ſet it in warme dung, or in <hi>Balneo Mariae,</hi> vntill it bee diſſolved; then diſtill it in ſand with a head and a receiver, &amp; thou ſhalt haue both Oyle and water,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14357:22"/>the which yee ſhall ſeparate one from another: ye ſhall underſtand, that there will come foorth more water then oyle, as I haue prooved many times.</p>
                     <p>This Oyle helpeth the Cough comming of moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture: it purgeth the breaſt, and helpeth Vlcers in that place, three or foure drops being taken in an Egge: it helpeth paines in the ſide, if yee annoynt it therewith: It diſſolveth all hardneſſe, and ſwellings, and taketh away the paynes of the Gowt. If ye mixe this oyle with as much oile of <hi>Galba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> and a very little oyle of Wormewood, and annoint the Milt, it taketh away all the paines: being mixed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14357:23"/>with oile of Wormewood, and annoynted in the navill, it killeth wormes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocolla.</head>
                     <p>THis is an excellent <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi> againſt all wounds, and filleth them with fleſh: it purgeth all olde ſores, without paine and ſmart: it breaketh hard Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumes, it helpeth all run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Eyes, if you vſe it in a Collirie: it helpeth wheales in the eye-lids: Being drunk with Wine, it helpeth the Phewme that falleth to the teeth, and for that cauſe it is vſed of thoſe that are troubled with aboundance of flegmatique humours:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14357:23"/>You ſhall note, that this oile is ſpecially vſed in freſh wounds, and old ſores. This Oyle is made as you made the oyle of <hi>Serapynum.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoreum.</head>
                     <p>TAke the fatteſt that thou canſt gett, and ſtampe it well; then put it into a glaſſe, and ſet it to putrifie in <hi>Balneo Mariae,</hi> fiue or ſixe dayes, then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill it with a ſoft fire, and thou ſhalt haue an excellent Oyle.</p>
                     <p>This is good againſt all cold Cramps, and Balſies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mixed with Rew and Vineger, and put into the noſtrills, it comforteth the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14357:24"/>braine, and taketh away paines of the head. Beeing annoynted on the necke, and alſo drunke with Wine, it helpeth much thoſe that are troubled with the Falling Sickneſſe: It helpeth Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions, and paines of the ſinewes, if you annoynt them therewith: Being drunk with Pepper and Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dromell, it provoketh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens termes, and alſo the fruit, it warmeth cold pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; it is alſo excellent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Appoplexia</hi> it helpeth thoſe that are deafe, it moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth Venery. It cureth the Collicke, and the ſuffocation of the Matrix, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theneth the naturall parts.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:14357:24"/>
                     <head>To make Oyles of Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe.</head>
                     <p>TAke <hi>Frankincenſe,</hi> as much as you will, and put it into a Retort of glaſſe well luted, and put thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to for every pound of ſtuffe, foure ounces of cleane ſand, and then diſtill it with a gentle fire, vntill all the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance bee come foorth, and thou ſhalt haue both water and oyle, the which ye muſt ſeparate.</p>
                     <p>The water is good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt wind in the ſtomack, if it bee drunke: it is alſo good for choppes in the hands and feet, if yee waſh them therewith, &amp; annoynt them with the oyle againſt the fire, and ſtrait wayes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14357:25"/>put on a paire of gloues, and ſo doing three times they ſhall be whole.</p>
                     <p>This Oile helpeth ſimple wounds in three or foure dayes, if yee annoynt them therewith, and lay thereon a cloath wet in the ſame, it preſerveth all fleſh from pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifying and alteration, and taketh away the paine: It helpeth all aches and bruiſes if ye anoint them therwith. Ye ſhall note, that you muſt vſe no tent where you occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie this oyle, but waſh the wound cleane, and joyne it, or ſtitch it cloſe together, and then lay thereon a cloth wet in the ſame; for if yee fall a tenting, ye make work for the Surgeon.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:14357:25"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine.</head>
                     <p>TAke pure and cleane <hi>Turpentine</hi> as much as you will, and put it into a glaſſe, ſo that three parts be emptie, and put therein a certaine quantitie of Sand, as much as you ſhall thinke good; then diſtill it in ſand with a ſoft fire, and there wil come foorth foure Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors: The one is a cleare water, the other a cleare Oyle, the third a yellow Oyle, the fourth a red and ſtinking, the which a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Potecaries doe fell in ſtead of <hi>Balme.</hi> Yee ſhall note, that the firſt Oyle is hot, the ſecond hotter, the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14357:26"/>third hotteſt of all, and not ſo good to occupie inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as the firſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Falopius</hi> in his booke of ſecrets writeth, that this oile will help freſh wounds in foure and twenty houres, if ye anoint them therwith, and lay thereon a cloath wet in the ſame. So is the oyle of Tile-ſtones, or the bleſſed oyle mixed with Grayes or Badgers greaſe. This oyle is made with powder of tyle-ſtones burnt redd hot, and quenched in the beſt oyle o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, and then with a retort and ſtrong fire purchaſed.</p>
                     <p>It is good againſt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or ſinews comming of cold: It provoketh vrine, if yee drinke one dram of the firſt oyle in white wine: it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14357:26"/>breaketh wind in the bodie, and diſſolveth the Pluriſie, and peſtilent Fever: it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voketh an appetite if ye an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynt the ſtomacke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. It helpeth againſt cold diſeaſes of the Maw, and helpeth a ſtinking breath, and the cough.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Wax.</head>
                     <p>TAke new yellow Waxe as much as you ſhal think good, and melt it on the fire; then powre it into ſweet Wine, and vvring it betweene your hands, then melt it againe, and powre it into Wine againe; and this you ſhall doe fiue or ſixe times at the leaſt, and everie time you muſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14357:27"/>haue freſh Wine, then at the laſt you ſhall put it into a Retort of glaſſe well luted with his Receiver, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill it in Sand, and there will come forth a faire yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low oyle, the which will congeale like pap when it is cold. You ſhall underſtand, that for everie pound of Waxe, yee ſhall put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to foure ounces of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Brickes into the glaſſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Raymonde Lullie</hi> greatly commendeth this Oyle, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooving it rather to bee a Celeſtiall or divine Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, then humane: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this in wounds wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth moſt miraculouſly, which for his marveilous commoditie, is not ſo well
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14357:27"/>to bee vſed of the common Chirurgion: Becauſe this precious Oyle healeth a vvound bee the ſame never ſo bigge or wide, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wide ſtitched vp, in the ſpace of eleven dayes, or twelue at the moſt: But thoſe that are ſmall, this Oyle healeth in three or foure dayes, by annoynting onely the wound therwith, and laying thereon a'cloath wet in the ſame.</p>
                     <p>Alſo for inward diſeaſes this Oyle worketh mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles: For if you giue one dramme at a time to drinke with white wine, it ſtayeth the ſhedding of the hayre, either on the head or beard, by anoynting the place ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. Moreover, it is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14357:28"/>in provoking of Vrine which is ſtopped: it helpeth ſtitches and paines in the loines, if you drink the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid quantitie with White Wine: It helpeth the cold Gowt or <hi>Sciatica,</hi> and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther griefes comming of cold. Yee ſhall underſtand, that if you rectifie this oile, it wil congeale no more, but then it will bee too hot to take inwardly, for it pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth marvellouſly, and is good to bee mixed with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther medicines, to cauſe them to pierce the better.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make the Quinteſſence of Honey.</head>
                     <p>YOu ſhall vnderſtand that Honey is a liquor rather divine then humane, becauſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14357:28"/>it falleth from heaven vpon the hearbs, &amp; is ſuch a ſweet thing, that the like cannot bee found vpon the earth. And this <hi>Raymond Lullie</hi> calleth the Flower of Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, becauſe Bees gather it vpon the Flowers in the field. And truely it is a moſt ſtrange thing if wee would conſider well the qualitie of Honey and Waxe: and therefore the wiſe <hi>Baruch Arabico,</hi> in the <hi>Academie</hi> of <hi>Avicene,</hi> did write this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: <hi>Mel dentro, &amp; olio difuori,</hi> ſatisfying vs by this, that Honey and Oyle were the firſt two liquors in the world. And truly it is ſo if we conſider well, as it may well bee prooved by holy Scripture.</p>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:14357:29"/>
                     <p>The order to make this <hi>Quinteſſence,</hi> is thus: Take two pound of perfect pure Honey, and put it into a great glaſſe, that foure parts of fiue may remaine emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: Lute it well with a Head and Receiver, and giue it fire vntill there appeare certain white fumes, which you ſhall turne into water, with wetting of clothes in cold water, and laying them on the Receiver and Head, and they will turne into wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a redd colour like blood. When it is all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled, keepe the glaſſe cloſe ſhut, and let it ſtand till it bee cleare, and in the colour of a Rubine. Then diſtill it in <hi>Bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Mariae,</hi> at leaſt ſixe or ſeven times, and ſo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14357:29"/>it will loſe his red colour, and remaine in the colour of Golde, having a great ſmell, and ſo pleaſant, that the like cannot bee found in the world.</p>
                     <p>The juice of a Limmon doeth diſſolue Leafe-golde in vvarme aſhes, with the <hi>Quinteſſence</hi> of this honey, and maketh it potable in fortie eight houres.</p>
                     <p>This <hi>Quinteſſence</hi> diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth gold, and maketh it potable, and likewiſe any ſort of Iewell that is put therein. It is of ſuch ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that if any bee a dying, and drinke two or three drammes thereof, preſently hee will recover, as the <hi>Quinteſſence</hi> of Wine will doe. If you waſh any wound
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14357:30"/>therewith, or other ſore, it will heale quickly. It is alſo good againſt the Cough, Catarre, and paines of the Milt, and many other diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which I will not ſpeake of: for but few. and they very hardly, wil beleeue the great vertue and operation thereof.</p>
                     <p>I gaue this ſix and fortie dayes vnto one that had the Palſie, and hee was holpen. It helpeth alſo the falling ſickneſſe, and preſerveth the bodie from putrifaction, ſo that by theſe you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that it is a celeſtiall medicine. If therefore anie vertuous man would take a little paine, in the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence heereof, hee ſhall doe wonderfull things, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14357:30"/>times I haue, ſo that the people deemed that I wrought by Inchantment, when as indeed I did it by vertue of this liquor, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the ſame ſo privily that they could not ſee it, which fell out to my great honour, and benefit of the ſicke, as you ſhall reade in my <hi>Theſauro della vita hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana.</hi> And therefore I would wiſh them that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Phyſicke and Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, to vſe ſuch Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, whereby commeth Honour and gaine to the Phyſician, and profite to the Patient.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:14357:31"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Lignum vitae, or Guaicum.</head>
                     <p>TAke the freſheſt Wood that thou canſt get, and make it in powder, then put it into a veſſell of glaſſe well luted, and ſet it in horſ-dung, or in <hi>Balneo,</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, then take it foorth, and diſtill it with a gentle fire, as thou wouldſt diſtill Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs, and thou ſhalt haue both oyle and water, the which thou ſhalt ſeparate by themſelues: then take the feces and put it into a new earthen pot, and ſet it in a furnace of reverberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vntill it bee burnt: into aſhes, then take that aſhes and make therof a Lie with
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14357:31"/>Fumetarie water, and when thou ſeeſt that the aſhes will make the water no more ſharpe, caſt them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and let the water ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle cleare, then vapour away the water with a ſoft fire, and in the bottome will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine a Salt, the which you ſhall diſſolue and congeale vntill it be cleare and faire, as <hi>Sal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ron,</hi> or <hi>Eniallie,</hi> then keepe it to thy uſe: the water is to drinke with Wine.</p>
                     <p>The Oyle is to annoynt the fores or aches, and the ſalt is to purge, and the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to vſe it is thus: Either in the Poxe, Gowt, or the Palſie.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, you ſhall purge the Patient wel with this: Take
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14357:32"/>of the ſalt halfe a ſcruple, <hi>Theriaca Alexandria,</hi> two drammes, mixe them, and giue them thereof halfe a ſcruple at a time: you ſhall giue this three or foure times, according to the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the diſeaſe; for in this Salt is vertue to purge all humours that cauſeth the Gowt, the Palſie, and the Poxe, and ſuch like hath not been found, neither by vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting or purging. Then when the patient is wel pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, if the patient haue any ſores or holes, you ſhall mundifie them with this ſalt; and when they are mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dified, you ſhall dreſſe them twiſe a day with the Oyle, vntill they bee whole, but if the Patient haue no holes,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14357:32"/>you ſhall annoynt thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where hee feeleth ache or griefe: Alſo every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning early in his bed, and at night an houre after ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, you ſhall giue him a good ſpoonefull of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with Renniſh wine to drinke, and let him ſweat thereon well; alſo hee ſhall vſe this with his meat if he will. Yee ſhall vnderſtand, that the cure lyeth not in meat nor drinke, but in the medicine, and therfore keep him not too hungry, but let him haue good meate, and well ſeaſoned with ſalt, and let him drinke wine; and ſo vſing this order, thou ſhalt be able to helpe the Gowt, Pox, or Palſie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:14357:33"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Butter.</head>
                     <p>TAke newe freſh But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as much as you will, and put it in a Retort of glaſſe well luted, and there will come forth three liquors, the which thou muſt ſeparate.</p>
                     <p>This Oyle doeth pearce marvellouſly, and taketh away the paines of the Gowt, if you annoint them therewith: If you annoint the hands and face there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, it will preſerue them faire: It is alſo good for thoſe that are troubled with a Catarre, if you giue them thereof an ounce faſting; for preſently it arriveth to the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14357:33"/>ſtomacke, and mollifieth the Catarre, in ſuch order as you ſhall ſpit it foorth at the mouth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Egges.</head>
                     <p>TAke Egges and ſeethe them hard; then take foorth the yelks, and ſtampe them in a morter, then put them in a frying-panne, and ſet them over the fire, and continually ſtirre them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till you ſee them turne to oyle, then take them forth, and put them into a Canvas bagge, and preſſe it foorth. This Oyle helpes wounds with great ſpeed: it makes the hayre of the head or beard black: It takes away the paines of the Emerodes;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14357:34"/>it is excellent againſt bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with fire, or ſcalding with water: you ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand this oyle may bee made very perfect by the art of Diſtillation without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, as I haue prooved divers times.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Here beginneth the Order to make Oyles of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Spices and Seeds.</head>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head type="sub">To make Oyle of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake Sinamon as much as you will, and ſtampe it groſſely; then put it into a glaſſe with pure
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14357:34"/>
                        <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> and ſo let it ſtand fiue or ſixe dayes, then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill it with a ſmall fire, and there will come forth both oyle and water, the which you ſhall ſeparate one from another, for the Oyle will ſinke to the bottome: ſome vſe to diſtill this with wine, and ſome with Roſe-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                     <p>You ſhall vnderſtand, that this Oyle is of a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veilous nature, for it pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth through the fleſh and bones, and is very hot and drie, and is good againſt all colde and moyſt diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and in ſpeciall for the heart and head, in ſo much that if a man lay ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and could ſcant draw his winde, it would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14357:35"/>recover him againe, ſo that his time bee not yet come: moſt miraculous to ſee: and to bee ſhort, this Oyle is of ſuch operation and vertue, that if a man drinke never ſo little, hee ſhall feele the working in his fingers and toes with great marvell: and therfore to be ſhort, it pierceth tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the whole body, and helpes all diſeaſes that are come through cold &amp; fleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matique matter. This oyle is hot and ſharpe: it digeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and makes thin, &amp; driues downe womens termes: it helpes vvomen that haue great paines and ſmart in their travaile, and brings foorth their fruite, if you giue the Patient a little of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14357:35"/>this Oyle, with oyle of Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra in Wine to drinke, and annoynt the parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. The face and hands being annoynted with this oyle, it driveth away the Meaſells and Spots. It war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the breaſt, and helpes the colde Cough: It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes all cold Fluxes, that proceed from the braine, and head, and cauſeth quiet ſleepe.</p>
                     <p>This Oyle may bee occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied in ſtead of the naturall Baulme for many Diſeaſes: Yee ſhall note, that the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Sinamon is alſo good againſt the aforeſayd Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, but yet nothing of ſo much force as the Oyle; for one drop of Oyle will doe more, then foure ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulls
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14357:36"/>of the vvater: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would bee vſed together.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Cloues.</head>
                     <p>THis Oyle is made in this order: Take the beſt Cloues thou canſt get, and beat them groſſely, then put them into pure wine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a glaſſe with a long neck cloſe luted; then ſet it in warme horſ-dung the ſpace of a moneth, then diſtill it in ſand with a ſoft fire, and thou ſhalt haue a faire Oyle, which will ſinke to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, the which you ſhall ſeparate: and his vertues are theſe.</p>
                     <p>It ſtrengtheneth the braine, head, and heart, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14357:36"/>reviveth the ſpirits; it ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth againſt al cold diſeaſes, it conſumeth all euil flegme: being outwardly applyed, it hath great vertue in healing, &amp; may be occupied in ſteed of balme for wounds. One or two droppes taken in the morning with wine helps a ſtinking breath: it maks the heart merry, and cleanſeth the filthineſſe thereof, and openeth the liver that is ſtopped: being put into the eye it cleeres the ſight, it comforts a cold ſtomacke, and cauſeth good digeſtion, it purgeth melancholy: this oyle may be made in <hi>manus Chriſti</hi> with ſugar, and they will haue the aforeſaid ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and ſtrength.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:14357:37"/>
                     <head>To make Oile of Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs.</head>
                     <p>THis Oyle is made as the Oyle of Cloues, and will ſwim vpon the wine: but if you diſtill this againe in <hi>Balneo,</hi> it will bee moſt pure and ſuttle, and may bee kept an hundred yeeres in his perfect ſtrength and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
                     <p>This Oyle being drunke with Wine, driveth downe womens tearmes, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the quicke and the dead fruit: and therefore wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with child ſhall not oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupie this oyle, vntill ſuch time as they bee in travell with childe, and then it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them to be faire delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14357:37"/>without paine and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: Being drunke with wine, it takes away al paines of the head comming of cold: It comforts the maw, and opens the liver, milt, and kidneyes, and ſuch like, it is excellent againſt beating of the heart, and faintneſſe and ſwouning; if ye drinke thereof, and annoint the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the heart therwith: it makes good blood, and expelleth flegmatique and melancholly humours, and makes a man merry: being vſed at night, it takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all fancies and dreames: if any had a vvound, or had broken a ribbe within him with a fall, let him drinke this Oyle with any ſlight wound-drinke, and it
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14357:38"/>will helpe him although he were almoſt dead: it is good in all filthy ſores which are counted uncurable: it is alſo pretious for all cold diſeaſes of the ioynts and ſinews: it makes a ſweet breath: if the ſplene doe ſwell, yee ſhall annoint therewith the left ſide: it helps all effects in the blather if it bee drunke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Mace.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle is made as aforeſaid, and is hot in operation, it hath great ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue againſt the chollicke, which commeth of cold cauſes, or of a rheume deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending from the head: it
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14357:38"/>comforts the heart, the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, and the wombe, it is good in the ſtrangurie, and all cold diſeaſes: if yee drinke thereof three or foure drops faſting with a ſpoonfull of wine or broath, or eate two or three <hi>manus Chriſti</hi> made there with.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Pepper.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle is diſtilled as is ſaid afore, and is very cleare and light, and his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are theſe.</p>
                     <p>This oyle hath more ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue then the Pepper hath in piercing, and ſpecially in the cholicke, and other weake places filled with flegme, if you take thereof three or
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14357:39"/>foure droppes with one ſcruple of the juyce of a Quince, two houres afore the fit, after the bodie is well purged, and let blood; it ſtayeth alſo the ſhaking at the firſt time, or elſe at the ſecond, it taketh away the fit.</p>
                     <p>Yee ſhall vnderſtand that this Oyle is onely the ayrie part, ſeparated from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Elements. I ſaw once this Oyle made by a Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which had the perfect taſte, ſavour, and ſmell, and was ſo hot on the tongue as oyle of Vitrioll.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:14357:39"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Saffron.</head>
                     <p>TAke the beſt Saffron thou canſt get, and put it into a glaſſe, and put thereon pure rectified <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> then lute the glaſſe faſt, and ſet it in warme horſe-dung a moneth: then diſtill it in <hi>Balneo Maria</hi> with a ſoft fire, vntill all the <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> be come foorth: then take foorth the Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, and preſſe it in a preſſe made for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, within a ſtrong Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſſe bagge, and you ſhall haue both oyle and water, which you ſhall diſgeſt fiue or ſixe dayes, and then ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them by art.</p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:14357:40"/>
                     <p>If this oyle bee drunken with Wine it makes a man merry, and to haue a faire colour: if yee annoint the temples of a man overcome with drinke it will helpe him. This oyle being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed on Saint <hi>Anthonies</hi> fire it quencheth it, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues the place: this oyle being mixed with womens milke ſtoppeth the running of the eyes: being annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the heart it maketh it merry. The head being annoynted with this oyle it provokes ſleepe, by reaſon whereof the ancient Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors heretofore did uſe it to ſuch as were mad, annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the temples therewith, it cleanſeth old ſores.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:14357:40"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Anniſeede.</head>
                     <p>TAke as much Anniſeed as thou wilt, and beate it groſly, then infuſe it in ſtrong wine foure or fiue dayes, and diſtill it in a gourd with a head and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, in ſand, and there will come forth both oyle and water, which thou ſhalt ſeparate.</p>
                     <p>This oyle being drunke with wine in the morning faſting, maketh a man to haue a ſweet breath, if ye put a little into the noſtrils when you goe to bed, and annoynt the temples there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: it takes away all paines comming of colde,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14357:41"/>and cauſeth the patient to ſleepe quietly: it is good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt winde in the gutts and ſtomacke, and cauſeth the paine to ceaſe, if yee drinke three or foure drops and annoynt the ſtomacke therewith: It breaketh al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Flegme, and cauſeth it to come foorth at the mouth: It provoketh ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous actes, and driveth foorth poyſon by ſweat: it is moſt excellent for thoſe that are ſhort winded, and cannot fetch their breath but with great paine: it comforteth the Breaſt and lungs: it breaketh the ſtone in the Reines and, Bladder: it is good againſt the Bloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy flixe &amp; piles. If any cheſt be annoynted therewith, it
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14357:41"/>will not ſuffer Moaths to breed therein.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell ſeed.</head>
                     <p>THis is made as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, and his vertues are theſe: It is moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent againſt all paines of the eyes, in ſo much that if a man were almoſt blinde, it would recover his ſight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if he drinke thereof once a day, and dropp one drop into the eye morning and euening: It maketh a ſweet breath, and comforts the head of cold humours: it comforteth the Maw, and opens the liver &amp; Milt that is ſtopped: It helpeth the dropſie &amp; yellow Iaundiſe,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14357:42"/>of what cauſe ſoever it bee: in hot diſeaſes ye muſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupy it with cold waters, and in cold diſeaſes with wine: <hi>Ex Philippo Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This oyle as writeth <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonimus,</hi> breaketh the ſtone in the reines, and provoketh menſtrue and vrine: it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth the ſtomacke and breaketh wind, this oyle may bee made in <hi>manus Chriſti,</hi> with ſugar, and is very pleaſant, and hath the ſelfe ſame vertue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min ſeed.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle is made as is aforeſaid, and is good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt wounds that pierce
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14357:42"/>the ſplene: it is alſo moſt excellent to ſcatter and breake all the windineſſe of the ſtomacke, the belly, the bowels and matrixe; alſo it is ſingular againſt gryping torments, and gnawings or frettings of the belly, not onely to bee vſed inwardly, but to be put into gliſters, or to bee layed to outwardly with barley meale. This oyle being drunke with wine, is good for thoſe that are hurt with any venemous beaſts: this oyle either eaten in <hi>Manus Chriſti,</hi> or drunke is very profitable for ſuch as haue the cough and haue taken cold, and for thoſe whoſe breaſts are charged or ſtopped. This oyle being too much vſed, decayeth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14357:43"/>the naturall complexion and liuely colour, cauſing one to looke wanne and pale.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raway ſeed.</head>
                     <p>THis Oyle is made in the aforeſaid order, and is very good and convenient for the Stomacke, and for the mouth: at helpeth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, and provoketh V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine: it ſwageth and diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth all kinde of windineſſe and blaſtings of the inward parts. And to conclude, it is anſwerable to the Oyle of Annis ſeed, in vertue and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:14357:43"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Dill ſeed.</head>
                     <p>THis Oyle is made in the aforeſaid order: This oyle being eaten in <hi>Manus Chriſti,</hi> or drunk with wine, cauſeth vvomen to haue great plentie of Milke: it driveth away ventoſitie or windineſſe, &amp; ſwageth the blaſtings &amp; griping torment of the belly: it ſtayeth vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting and laskes, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voketh vrine: it is very profitable againſt the ſuffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or ſtrangling of the matrix, if yee cauſe the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to ſit over the fume of it in a cloſe ſtoole, for that purpoſe this oyle being ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>Manus Chriſti,</hi> ſtaieth the yexe or hiquet.</p>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:14357:44"/>
                     <p>This oyle healeth hollow and moiſt ulcers, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the ſhare or pvivie parts, this oyle doth digeſt and reſolue and ſwage paine, and ripeneth all raw and unripe humours. This oyle may not bee too much vſed inwardly, for it diminiſheth the ſight, and the ſeed of generation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Parce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeed.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle is made in the aforeſaid order, and his vertues is to open obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the liver and kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: it provoketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue, if it bee drunke with convenient liquors: it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a good appetite and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14357:44"/>diſgeſtion, and comforts the ſtomacke: it driueth forth the ſtone and gravell, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoketh vrine, and is a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt all poiſons: it dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth away all blaſtings and windineſſe: it is alſo good againſt the Cough, if it bee made with medicines made for that purpoſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Rue, or Hearbgrace.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle is made of the ſeed of Rue being putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in wine.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cardanus,</hi> writeth, that this Oyle being perfectly made, is of great vettue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt poyſon being drunke with wine, for it cauſeth the patient to avoyd it by
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14357:45"/>vomit, at the firſt time hee taketh it: and at the ſecond time it expelleth the other evill humours that are infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted therewith: and at the third time it cureth the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and maketh him whole: and this is done in three or foure daies: it helpeth all diſeaſes of the eyes, of what cauſe ſoever it be, ſo that the apple of the eye be not peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. The vſe of this oile to the eye, is to annoint it ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with twice a day, or waſh the eye with the water of Rue, and drop one or two drops into the eye.</p>
                     <p>This oyle being drunke, ſuffereth no poyſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in man that day: if a man drinke thereof faſting which is ſore wounded, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:14357:45"/>that the other cure bee had accordingly, hee ſhall eaſily eſcape. This oyle being drunke, taketh away the gowt and dropſie ſprung of a cold cauſe: it reſtores all nummed members taken with the Palſie, if you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynt them therewith.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cardanus</hi> alſo affirmeth in his ſecond booke <hi>de Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitate,</hi> that there are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine poyſons which ſlay with their onely touching, againſt which poyſon, ſaith he, the beſt remedy is, not to tarry in any place vntill thy hand waxe hot, but often bathe the parts with warme water, and annoynt them with oyle of Rue perfectly diſtilled.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:14357:46"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Ivie.</head>
                     <p>THis Oyle is made as is aforeſaid, and is good againſt theſe Diſeaſes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
                     <p>Againſt gripings or wind in the gutts: againſt <hi>Gono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rheam,</hi> &amp; paines in the neck comming of a Catarre: this oyle may bee compared to Balme, three or foure drops being drunke, it doeth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the reſolution of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, the Falling ſickneſſe, and other Diſeaſes of the braine: It preſerveth the body from all poyſon and peſtilent ayres, it comforts a colde ſtomacke: It ſtayeth vomiting: it purgeth the reines: it breakes the ſtone,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14357:46"/>it provoketh Vrine: it hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the Collick, and paines of the guttes: it helpeth paines in the Stomacke and Lungs: it is good againſt the Dropſie, and water be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the skinne and the fleſh: it killeth wormes: to bee ſhort, it helpeth all ſicke members: by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his piercing, being anoynted outwardIy, it ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Conſumptions: it hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth Scabbes, and olde evill Vlcers: it: helpeth paines of the hippes, the Gowt, and Collicke: It helpeth the choppes in the handes and feete.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Philippus Harmanus</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that if this Oyle bee rectified againe, it will bee an hundred times more pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14357:47"/>and more piercing, for I haue ſeene thoſe that could not make water in three or foure dayes: and after they haue drunke foure or fiue drops of this oyle, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted therewith the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the bladder, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they haue made water without any tarying.</p>
                     <p>This Oyle is ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent againſt the Peſtilence, that if any drinke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of oftentimes, hee ſhall not bee infected: although he were in the houſe where the Peſtilence is. But if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny haue the Plague already, let him drink three or foure droppes in Wine, and lay him downe to ſweat, and the next day he ſhall be wel againe.</p>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:14357:47"/>
                     <p>This oyle is ſo excellent againſt poyſon, that if a man vſe it, there will no poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon remaine with him: It ſtrengtheneth the Maw and all inward parts, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally it warmeth the heart: it ſtoppeth the bloody flux: It is alſo good againſt all diſeaſes of the Kidneys and Bladder: If yee drinke it with Wine, it ſtoppeth wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens termes: this oyle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing annoynted from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell of a woman to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie parts and reines of the backe, it ſtrengtheneth the Matrix, or Mother, and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up the moyſture there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and prepareth it to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</p>
                     <p>This ſayd Oyle of Ivie being made up with Sugar
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14357:48"/>in <hi>Manus Christi,</hi> hath the foreſaid vertues.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oile of Roſemary Flowers.</head>
                     <p>TAke Roſemary Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and ſtampe them, then put it into a glaſſe with ſtrong Wine, and ſtop it cloſe, then ſet it in the Sun fiue or fixe dayes, and then diſtill it with a ſoft fire, and thou ſhalt haue both water and oyle, the which you ſhal ſeparate, and keepe cloſe in a glaſſe, and his vertues are theſe.</p>
                     <p>It helpeth againſt all paines in the head, although they haue continued ſeaven yeares: it comforteth the memorie, &amp; alſo preſerveth
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14357:48"/>the eyes, if you drinke thereof now and then a drop or two, and put ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the eyes. It hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth thoſe that are deafe, if it be put into the eares, and alſo drunke with good wine: It openeth all ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings of the liver and milt, and helpeth againſt the dropſie and yellow Iaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize: it breaketh wind and helpeth the Cholicke, and riſing of the mother: it is alſo excellent for thoſe that haue drunke poiſon, or that are infected with the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, if you drinke thereof a little and lay you downe to ſweat: It comforteth the heart and cleanſeth the blood, and maketh a man merry, and cauſeth a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14357:49"/>good colour, and this Oyle is moſt excellent for thoſe that are full of Itch, and ſcabbes. And to bee ſhort, it helpeth all the diſeaſe of the body, that come of cold and moyſt humours, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were never ſo evill: It helpeth the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and Fiſtulaes, and ſuch like.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Wild Time.</head>
                     <p>THis Oyle is made as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
                     <p>This Oylebeing eaten in Tablets of Sugar, or drunke in Wine, bringeth to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men their fluxe naturall, and driveth out the front and gravell, and provoketh vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14357:49"/>the ſame taken in like manner ſtoppeth the Laske, and cureth Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings or gnawings, and is excellent againſt Crampes, and the contraction of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes.</p>
                     <p>This Oyle being taken in meats or broaths, is a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne Medicine againſt all poiſons, and againſt the bitings and ſtingings of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous beaſts and ſerpents. This being applied unto the forehead and temples with oyle of Roſes and vineger, ſwageth headach, and is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good againſt raving and frenzie: the fume of this Oyle driveth away vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous beaſts.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:14357:50"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Time.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle is made as is aforeſaid, and his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are theſe.</p>
                     <p>Three or foure drops be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drunke with honied water, helpeth a painefull cough and ſhortneſſe of breath: it provoketh vrine, and expelleth the ſecondine and dead fruit from the matrixe: it provoketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue, and diſſolveth clotted and congeled blood in the body: being taken with oximell and a little ſalt, it purgeth tough and clammie flegme, and ſharpe chole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke humours, and all the corruption of the blood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:14357:50"/>being taken in the ſaid man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, it is good againſt the <hi>Sciatica,</hi> the paine in the ſide and the breaſt: it is alſo good againſt blaſtings and windineſſe in the ſide and belly, and of the ſtones and genitors: it is good for thoſe that are fearefull, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, and troubled in ſpirit and mind.</p>
                     <p>This oyle being often v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, helpeth bleered eyes and paines of the ſame: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drunke in wine, it is moſt profitable for thoſe that are troubled with the Gowt, but if it chance that their paines be on them, yee ſhal giue them 5 or 6 drops with a dram of oximell: if ye uſe this oftentimes with honey, it will cleanſe the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14357:51"/>breaſt, and ripen flegme, and cauſeth it to bee ſpit foorth with eaſe: the ſmell of this Oyle is moſt comfortable for thoſe that haue the Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſickneſſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of ſweet Margerom.</head>
                     <p>THis Oyle is made as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and his vertues are theſe.</p>
                     <p>Being drunke in White Wine, it is moſt whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for thoſe that beginne to fall into a dropſie, and for ſuch as cannot piſſe but drop after drop, and that with great difficultie. It is alſo good for thoſe that are troubled with griping pains
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14357:51"/>and wringings of the belly: being taken in the ſaid or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, it provoketh womens tearmes.</p>
                     <p>If yee convey this Oyle with Oyle of bitten Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds up into the noſtrils, it will purge the head of moyſt humors, and cauſe them to ſneeſe. It is moſt excellent for thoſe that have loſt their ſmelling, &amp; againſt all paines of the head, being vſed as is aforeſaid: It is good againſt poyſon, and the ſtining of Scorpions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:14357:52"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Sage.</head>
                     <p>This oyle is made in the aforeſaid order: And helpeth congealed blood within the body, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth inward wounds and bruſes, either by a ſtripe or fall if it bee drunke with wine: it provoketh vrine and breaketh the ſtone: it comforteth the heart, and taketh away the head ache. It is alſo good for women with child, to uſe it now and then, for it cloſeth the matrixe and comforteth the fruite.</p>
                     <p>This oyle being often drunke cauſeth women to bee fruitfull: If yee drinke
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14357:52"/>it with wine it helpeth the cough, and openeth the ſtoppings of the Liver, and ſwageth the paine in the ſide: if it be drunke with worme-wood wine, it ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the bloody flixe: It is alſo good againſt the biting of venemous beaſts, for it cleanſeth and helpeth them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neriall.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle is made as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and his vertues are theſe.</p>
                     <p>Being drunke in Wine, it mooveth monethly tearms, bringeth forth the ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, the dead fruite and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:14357:53"/>the vnnaturall birth: it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voketh urine, and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Stone, eſpecially in the Kidneyes, being uſed with purified Honey: It cleanſeth the Lungs and Breaſt from all groſſe and thicke humours. This oyle being mixt with Honey and Aloes, purgeth the melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholick humour, and prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth much againſt Crampes, and the contraction of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes.</p>
                     <p>This oyle being drunke with water and Vineger, ſtayeth the inordinate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to vomite, and the gnawing paines of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke; being drunke with Wine, it helpeth the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of venemous beaſtes: it is alſo good againſt the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:14357:53"/>Falling Sickneſſe: the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and noſtrills being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted with this oyle, it taketh away the ſwimming paines and giddineſſe of the head. It is moſt excellent for thoſe that haue cold and moyſt braines: it taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the paines of the Gowt, The fume or ſmoke of this Oyle being at the ſecret parts with a fonnell, is good againſt ventoſitie, windineſſe, and blaſtings, and alſo againſt the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſtopping of the Mother.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:14357:54"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Mint.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle is made as is aforeſaid.</p>
                     <p>This oyle being either eate or drunke, is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the ſtomacke, for it warmeth and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſame, and drieth up all moiſt and ſuperfluous humours gathered in the ſame, and taketh away all paines thereof, and cauſeth good digeſtion: it ſtaieth alſo vomiting in thoſe that haue a weake ſtomacke, being drunke with vineger, it ſtayeth thoſe that vomite blood, and killeth the round wormes.</p>
                     <p>This oyle being drunke
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:14357:54"/>foure or fiue times with ſome convenient liquor, hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the griping paine and gnawing in the belly, with the Collicke, and ſtoppeth the inordinate courſes of the menſtruall iſſue, being drunke with wine, it ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth women which are too much grieved with hard and perillous travel in child bearing: being dropped in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the eares it taketh away the paine: the ſmell of this oyle cauſeth a man to bee merry.</p>
                     <p>This oyle is ſingular good againſt the gravell and ſtone in the Kidnies, and againſt the ſtrangury, which is when one cannon piſſe, but drop after drop, if yee uſe to drinke it in wine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:14357:55"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Iſope.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle is made as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid of Camomill. If ye uſe to eate this oyle either mixed with honey, or made into <hi>Manus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti</hi> with Sugar, it will helpe thoſe that haue obſtructions or ſtoppings of the breaſt, with ſhortneſſe of breath, it is alſo good againſt an old difficult and hard cough: yee muſt uſe this morning and evening for a certaine ſpace.</p>
                     <p>This oyle being drunke with ſirope of vineger, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth downe-ward tough and clammie flegme, and killeth and driveth forth
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:14357:55"/>wormes: it hath the like vertue if yee eate the ſame with figges.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh ſeed.</head>
                     <p>TAke the ſeed of Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh and ſtampe it ſmall, then take for every pound of ſeed, two ounces of good Wine, then ſtampe it againe untill it be mixed, then put it into a veſſell of Iron or Copper, and ſet it over the fire, and ſtirre it continually, untill it bee as hot as you may ſuffer your hand therein, and then put it into a canvas bagge, and preſſe it forth, and thou ſhalt haue both oyle and water,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:14357:56"/>the which you ſhall ſeparate one from another.</p>
                     <p>This oyle cauſeth good digeſtion, and provoketh vrine, the which is ſtopped through wind and ventoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: it diſſolveth wind in the ſtomacke, and breaketh the gravell and ſtone in the bladder.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard ſeed.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle is made by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion as is ſaid afore, and is excellent for thoſe that haue the ſtone, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them to avoid gravell: it provoketh womens ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, if you annoint the body and reines, and within the necke of the Matrixe,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:14357:56"/>and alſo take it inwardly, it diſſolveth the paines of the ſide and mother, if you eate it with a little Sinamon and white Honey mixed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort ſeed.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle is made as is ſaid afore, and of nature is hot and windy, and is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed much of lecherous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, becauſe it maketh ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the yard, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them to bee luſty, being vſed in meates it cauſeth good digeſtion: it preſerveth armour from ruſting a long time it is good againſt inflamations
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:14357:57"/>in all parts of the body, and is alſo good againſt wormes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Linſeed.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle is made in the aforeſaid order, and is good againſt the pluriſie: if yee giue thereof foure ounces to drinke, for it diſſolveth the impoſtume preſently, and ſo preſerveth life. It is good againſt Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods in the fundament. This oyle of Linſeed being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled with Frankencenſe and waxe, is moſt excellent to diſſolue all contuſions. With this oyle they make verniſh.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:14357:57"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Woort or Seed.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle is made of the ſeeds by impreſſion, and is excellent to helpe wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, becauſe it defendeth them from alteration, and matura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and will not ſuffer hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours to run thither. It is alſo excellent againſt poiſon, and the peſtilent fever, and all evill diſpoſitions of the ſtomacke: it is good againſt the fluxe of the body and Emerods, and for all manner of ſcabs. It helpeth the rupture newly done, if you annoynt it therewith, and weare a truſſe fit for the purpoſe, and let him keepe
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:14357:58"/>his bed, and walke as little as hee can for a certaine time: it helpeth againſt all manner of ſores, as well old as new, and that it doth by his proper quality, for it is neither hot nor cold, but temperate.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſeed.</head>
                     <p>TAke the ſeed of Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and ſtampe them, then put them into a frying pan with a little wine, and ſtirre them well together, untill it bee ſo hot that you can ſcarce abide your hand therein, then put it into a canvas bag, and preſſe it out in a preſſe, and thou ſhalt haue both oyle and water,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:14357:58"/>the which thou ſhalt ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</p>
                     <p>This oyle is excellent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all paines in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, and helpeth the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion &amp; diſſolveth wind: It provoketh venerous acts. It is alſo good againſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merods and Fiſtulaes that come in the lower parts.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Acornes.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle is made as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and is very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictiue and driving, and helpeth thoſe that are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with the fluxe, if yee drinke thereof a little and anoynt the belly therewith: you ſhall note that this oyle is not to bee occupied much inwardly: this oyle is excellent to make Verniſh</p>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:14357:59"/>
                     <p>In this manner yee make oyles out of all manner of feeds.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare by diſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
                     <p>Take white <hi>Tartare</hi> bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in pouder, foure pound, and put it into a ſtrong veſſell of ſtone well luted, with a head and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, and giue it firſt a ſmall fire, and then increaſe it according to art, and at the laſt giue it extreame fire un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till all the moiſture be come forth, then put the liquor into a glaſſe, and diſtill it in <hi>Balneo,</hi> and the oyle will remaine in the bottome: the which thou ſalt diſtill
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:14357:59"/>or rectifie in ſand, and then the oyle will haue the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of gold.</p>
                     <p>It is moſt excellent to cure ulcers cauſed of the poxe: for it taketh away their malice in ſuch order, that it can hurt no more: being drunke with wine, it breaketh the ſtone in the raines and bladder, it provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vrine, it purgeth ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Another way to make Oyle of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare.</head>
                     <p>TAke <hi>Tartare</hi> and ſtamp it ſmall, and then put it in a new earthen pot ungla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed, and ſet it in a potters furnace, or furnace of rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:14357:60"/>untill it bee white, then lay it upon a ſmooth ſtone in a moiſt place, and it will turne into oyle: the which is corroſiue: but one part thereof mixed with ten parts of pure rectified <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> healeth ulcers quickly, if yee touch them therewith: it maketh the face faire: if yee waſh the haire therewith it maketh it yellow: it taketh out blacke ſpots in linnen cloth, and fixeth the medicines alchimicall, with divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertues, the which I will leaue untill another time.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:14357:60"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of a Harts horne.</head>
                     <p>YEe ſhall take a Harts horne in the moneth of Auguſt, and file it to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, then boyle it in water untill it be ſufficient, then draw away the water in <hi>Balneo,</hi> and take that which remaineth in the bottome, and put it in a glaſſe with little pieces of tiles, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill it, and thou ſhalt have a faire oyle, the which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth for ſundry purpoſes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:14357:61"/>
                     <head>To diſtill Oyle of a mans Excrements.</head>
                     <p>TAke the doung of a young ſanguine child or man, as much as you will, and diſtill it twice in a Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becke of glaſſe. This hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the Canker, and molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth Fiſtulaes: comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thoſe that are troubled with Allopecia.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To make Oyle of the Skull of a man.</head>
                     <p>TAke the skull of a man that was never buried, and beate it into powder, then diſtill away the fleg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> with a gentle fire, and put it on againe, and diſtill it again,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:14357:61"/>and this you ſhall doe three times upon the feces, and at the laſt give it ſtrong fire, untill the Oyle bee come foorth: the which yee ſhall ſeparate by <hi>Balneo,</hi> and keep it cloſe ſhut in a glaſſe. The doſe is three graines, againſt the falling ſickeneſſe. Yee ſhall underſtand, that there is alſo a ſalt to bee drawne forth of the feces, the which is of great vertue againſt the aforeſaid diſeaſes being drunke with wine, as is aforeſaid.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14357:62"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14357:62"/>
                  <p>SECRETS OF PHISICKE AND PHILO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SOPHIE.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſecond Booke,</hi> CONTAINING The ordering and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of all Mettalls, Mineralls, Allumes, Saltes, and ſuch like, for medicines both inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and outvvardly, and for divers other uſes.</p>
                  <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Will. Lugger,</hi> and are to be ſould at the <hi>Poſterne gate</hi> at <hi>Tower-Hill.</hi> 1633.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14357:63"/>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:14357:63"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Booke (welbeloved Reader) I have taken upon mee to ſet foorth, the true and worthy cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the diſtillation of Mineralles, that is, of thoſe things which are found in the Mines, as all
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:14357:64"/>manner of Salts, Allums, Vitrioll, Sulphur, Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſuch like Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles, as <hi>Saturnus, Iupiter, Mars, Sol, Luna, Venus.</hi> And how you ſhall get the liquor or moiſture out of them. And all that which appertaineth to the health of man. The which I meane by the grace of God to ſet foorth in this Booke, with a number of Alchy miſtes preparations of the ſaid things, the which worketh wonderfully in mans body: ſo that it ſeemeth to divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons myraculous.</p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:14357:64"/>
                  <p>Therfore (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) peruſe this Booke with diſcretion, and then if thou ſeeſt it ſtand to thy minde, ſet thy hand to the plough and be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in the worke, ſo that thou mayeſt know the proofe, and feele the ready commoditie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for yee ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that there is no me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine in the world that can be found of ſo quicke operation as the Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls are, if they bee truely prepared and as I will ſhew you here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: but if they be not well prepared they
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:14357:65"/>are very hurtfull, and not to bee allowed. Therefore looke that ye prepare them as I ſhall ſhew you, and then you ſhall wonder at their working.</p>
                  <p>And although the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſcience of <hi>Alchimie</hi> is come in ſuch diſdaine through lewd perſons, that it ſeemeth lyes and fables, and no true ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: Yet that ought not to hinder or derogate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to our purpoſe, as long as our matter is againſt the abuſe of it, as for example:</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Alchymiſtes</hi> have
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:14357:65"/>wrought in this worke, to the intent they might have of Lead and Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Gold and Silver, or the meane to make them of all other ſimples or ſlight mettalles. But whether God hath given them that gift I know not: therefore I leave it to the Maſters of that Arte. And albeit wee have ſeene many won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull things in that Arte: yet will I not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that it is poſſible to be done, for it ſeemeth vnreaſonable, that a man in ſo ſhort time ſhould doe that thing the which
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:14357:66"/>nature doth in many yeares. And that men ſhould preſume to doe that which God doth only himſelfe, and not any of his creatures. Wee therefore will not affirme it to bee true or poſsible, nor yet will wee deny it vtterly or condemne it as untrueth. But wee will leave the anſwer to thoſe that take it to be done.</p>
                  <p>But heere in this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe wee will ſet foorth that which we have ſeen and wrought, and proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and are expert therein: And although it
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:14357:66"/>bee ſprung out of the Arte of <hi>Alchymie,</hi> yet it is not to that intent, for it ſerveth not to tranſmute Mettalles, but it ſerveth to helpe thoſe diſeaſed both inwardly and outwardly, who of the common ſort of Chirurgions are counted uncurable, and alſo given over of the Phyſitians. Thoſe Patients ſhall be holpen through the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den myſteries &amp; heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſecrets of this ſcience.</p>
                  <p>And foraſmuch as it is unpoſsible to prepare theſe things without the Arte of <hi>Alchymie:</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:14357:67"/>we muſt praiſe this art through our preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons above al other ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that maketh for the health of man, for they preſerue a man only tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and afflicted with ſlight wounds and griefes on his body, and that with much paine and much adoe. But this Arte giveth unto man his health againe in ſhort time, and with ſmal paine unto the patient, be he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo deſperately ſicke, and to mans thinking paſt cure: for I have ſeene myracles therein.</p>
                  <p>And inſomuch that it
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:14357:67"/>is all prepared with fire: the meane man calleth it <hi>Alchymia.</hi> Howbeit the intent of the <hi>Alchymiſt</hi> is farre from our intent. But call it what you will, it maketh not much mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the name. For I am ſure there is nothing in all Phyſicke that mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth eyther better or readier helpe to cure mans body, then this ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of preparing mettals with fire rightly. I ſay rightly prepared, not as the unskilfull <hi>Apoticaries</hi> have ordered them, or as the unlearned Phyſitians have occupied them, for
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:14357:68"/>the <hi>Apoticary</hi> is no other then a ſervant in the kitchin (as I may terme him) and no maſter Cooke, ſo long as hee knoweth not theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, which I will ſhew you.</p>
                  <p>In like maner it is to be thought of the Phyſitian that hath no skill in theſe preparations. For wee have ſeene and prooved divers times, that the firſt vapour or ſmoake of any Herbe or Spice is the beſt that is therein, and yet our learned Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians commaund it to be boyled untill halfe be
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:14357:68"/>conſumed, &amp;c. Then note if the beſt flie away in boyling, what ſtrength can the Medicine have. Therefore I ſay that the Phyſitian without this Arte of preparation is little or nothing worth, although they take the patients money. For he goeth to worke blindly with a blinde leader, which is the Apoticary. But the Phyſitian that is expert in this Science, and doeth prepare his Medicines truely, hee is to be prayſed above all other. For a man cannot buy with any money
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:14357:69"/>that which is got by long carefull travell. Therefore is the Arte of <hi>Alchymie</hi> worthy to be praiſed, and the <hi>Alchymiſt</hi> to bee praiſed alſo, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they attaine not to their firſt intention, yet they have opened the way through the which this excellent cunning of preparation was knowne and found, and through the which there are a number of wonderfull ſecrets opened, the which without this Arte were all unknown, to the great hinderance of the ſicke and diſeaſed perſons.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:14357:69"/>Therfore I wil not ſpeak againſt it, but hold it in great eſtimation to our intention, that is the help of the ſicke and diſeaſed perſon, and to prepare the Mineralles where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you may doe that which cannot bee done with any other Hearbs, or ſimples, or ſpices And heerewith will we finiſh this preface, and write of the names of the ſimples, which are occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this Arte.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14357:70"/>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:14357:70"/>
                  <head>The names of the <hi>Mettals, Simples,</hi> or <hi>Medicines</hi> of this Science.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere will I wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloved Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſhew thee for good will that thing w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> many have ſought with their money and labour, and yet could never finde it: eſpecially for that I will not have this worthy Science trod under feete. Therefore
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:14357:71"/>wee will write firſt of the names of the Simples, and then of the names of the preparations, and what they are.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sal Armoniacke,</hi> that is a ſalt ſo called, the which yee ſhall finde at the Apoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sal Gemme,</hi> is ſtone ſalt, found in the Myne as cleere as the glaſſe.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sal Commune,</hi> is common ſalt that we eate.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vitriolum,</hi> is greene cope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Calcantum,</hi> is yellow Coperas, a matter like O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Alumen</hi> is Allum: but there are divers kinds.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sulfur Vive,</hi> is the ſtone whereout the other <hi>Sulfur</hi>
                        <pb n="119" facs="tcp:14357:71"/>is melted, and is greene of colour.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Antimonium</hi> is a certaine Minerall ſo called that yee ſhall finde at the Apotica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Carrabe</hi> that is yellow <hi>Ambre</hi> or <hi>Sucinum.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tartarum,</hi> that is Argil or wine leeſe.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Saturnus</hi> that is lead.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iupiter</hi> that is tinne.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mars</hi> that is yron.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sol</hi> that is gold.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Luna</hi> that is ſilver.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Venus</hi> that is copper.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mercury</hi> that is quick-ſilver.</item>
                  </list>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="120" facs="tcp:14357:72"/>
                     <head>The names of the preparations.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>CAlcinatio</hi> that is to make any of theſe mettalles as it were lime, with great fire ſometimes, and other ſometime with ſmall fire.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Solutio</hi> that is to diſſolve and make as it were liquid like unto water, the hard or tough ſubſtance of any thing.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sublimatio</hi> that is a dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving up, or aſcenſion of the mettall by force of heate into the toppe of the Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becke, ſo that it may hange in the top of the veſſell hard and dry.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Diſtillatio</hi> that is to take
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:14357:72"/>away the moyſture by the heate of the fire.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Digeſtio</hi> that is to ſet the matter in hot water or in horſe dung.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Fixatio</hi> that is to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime a matter, ſo long that it will ſublime no more, but remaine fixt in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome.</item>
                        <item>There are a number of other preparations, but we will leave them becauſe we have written ſufficient for our purpoſe already.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:14357:73"/>
                     <head>To prepare Crocum martis and ſuch like which are prepared through calcination.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>CRocum Martis,</hi> or <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eneris</hi> ſhall bee made in this manner: Take the limmall of yron, as much as you will, and waſh it with faire water ſo long untill that the water run as cleare as it was put out, then put it in a glaſſe, and put thereon ſtrong Vineger untill it bee covered, and let it ſtand ſo two or three dayes cloſe ſhut: then poure off the Vineger and dry the lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall well, then put it into a new earthen pot with a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and lute it very well
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:14357:73"/>round about with lime and haire mixt together: then ſet it in a furnace of calcina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion eight dayes and eight nights, ſo that it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſtand red hot, then take it foorth and grinde it on a ſtone, and if it grinde very ſmooth without any hard matter that yee can ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſee or feele, then it is calcined enough: but if yee feele any hard matter, put it into the furnace againe two or three dayes, and then grinde it againe, and this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ye ſhall uſe untill it bee fine as can be poſſible.</p>
                     <p>This <hi>Crocum Martis</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo prepared, amongſt all other medicines in the world, it is the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent that can bee found
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:14357:74"/>againſt the bloody flixe, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it in this order. Take conſerue of roſes one ounce, <hi>crocum Martis</hi> one ſcruple, mixe them together, and let the Patient eate it in the morning, and faſt thereon two houres, and it will helpe him although he had had it never ſo long, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo ſore. It is alſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven aboue all other medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines in the later end of a dropſie, and alſo againſt the fluxe of menſtrue, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt bleeding at the noſe, and all other fluxes. It hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth thoſe that ſpit blood: it is excellent to ſtop the fluxe in wounds, and to helpe them and dry them, if yee ſtrew the powder thereon, &amp;c. Yee ſhall
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:14357:74"/>make <hi>Crocum Veneris</hi> in the ſelfe ſame order aforeſaid: but where yee tooke lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall, yee ſhall take the ſcales of copper: and yee ſhall note, that this <hi>Crocum Veneris</hi> is not to bee vſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, but onely outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the preparation of Alumes and Salts</head>
                     <p>TAke <hi>ſal Gemme,</hi> or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſalt, and ſet it in a calcining furnace with a ſmall fire, untill it be red hot the ſpace of halfe an houre, and that it crake no more, then let it waxe cold and beate it to powder and let it melt, and let it ſtand till it be cleare; then powre it in a pot well nealed, and ſet it on the fire, and let it boyle
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:14357:75"/>till it be dry, and ye ſhall find the ſalt on the ground as white as ſnow, the which yee ſhall neale once more in the fire, and then it is prepa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The preparation of Allum.</head>
                     <p>TAke Allum and calcine it in an open veſſell till all his moyſture bee gone, then make it red hot, and after a while put it into an other pot with ſtrong vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ſet it on the fire and let it ſeeth dry, then ſet it on the fire againe till it bee red hot, and as white as ſnow, then keepe it to thy vſe.</p>
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:14357:75"/>
                     <p>This is very excellent to dry up old ſores if it bee mix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> with hony, and taketh away dead fleſh without payne, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To calcine Vitrioll.</head>
                     <p>TAke <hi>Vitrioll</hi> and beate it to powder, and put it into a new earthen pot that is unneiled, and ſet it in an oven ſomewhat warme till it be dry, then cover the pot cloſe and lute it well, that no aire may come forth: then ſet it in a calci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning furnace the ſpace of two houres, ſo that it may alwaies bee as red as the coles, and then it will bee as red as blood, then grind it on a ſtone, and keep it to thy uſe.</p>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:14357:76"/>
                     <p>There is no Coroſiue the which worketh like this <hi>vitrioll</hi> calcinated, for if yee mixe it with any Vnguent, and lay it on a ill Vlcer, it maketh an Asker the which in all coroſiues muſt be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with fat or butter: but this coroſiue needeth not, for yee muſt ſtill lay more therein, and leaue the Asker in the ſore, for the vertue of this <hi>Vitrioll</hi> is ſo great, that it cauſeth the fleſh to grow under the Asker, and when the fleſh is enough the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker will fall off, and then yee ſhall need nothing but to skin it, the which is not commonly ſeene of other coroſiues: therefore I praiſe this for the beſt of all coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiues.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="129" facs="tcp:14357:76"/>
                     <head>To calcine Quicksilver.</head>
                     <p>TAke <hi>Aqua fortis</hi> 
                        <seg rend="greek-xi">
                           <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>
                        </seg>. ii. <hi>Mercury</hi> 
                        <seg rend="greek-xi">
                           <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>
                        </seg>. i. and put them in a glaſſe, and ſet it on the fire in a ſcarvell with ſand or aſhes, till the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> be diſſolved, then put it into an earthen pot well glaſed, and ſet it on the fire to boyle till it bee dry, and ſtirre it alwayes with a ſticke that it may dry the better, and when as it is wel dryed, put it in an other pot with a kever that is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well glaſed within, then lute it very wel that no aire may come forth: but ye muſt note that the pot muſt be top full, then ſet it in a calcining Furnace with a good fire
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:14357:77"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="129" facs="tcp:14357:77"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="128" facs="tcp:14357:78"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="129" facs="tcp:14357:78"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="130" facs="tcp:14357:79"/>foure dayes &amp; foure nights, then grind it to ſmall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der on a ſtone, and keepe it to thy uſe. For thou haſt <hi>Mercurie</hi> calcinated, of the which wee have ſpoken much in our pearle of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie.</p>
                     <p>This is excellent in all olde ſores, although they be never ſo evill, for it clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth without paine and healeth them, that is, it clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth as long as it is needfull, and then it healeth, which is moſt ſtrange to ſee: this eateth away all dead fleſh, and preſerveth that which is good and ſound, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ulceration to heale in ſhort ſpace. Yee ſhall note that when wee ſpeake of <hi>Mercurie</hi> calcinated or
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:14357:79"/>precipitate in any place, yee ſhall take this.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To calcine Tartare.</head>
                     <p>TAke good <hi>Tartare</hi> that is cleere and without filth, and ſtamp it to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, then put it in a ſcravell that never was occupied, and ſet it in the calcining furnace, ſo that it may ſtand but even red hot, and there let it remaine untill it be as white as ſnow throughout, then take it forth and keepe it in a glaſſe cloſe ſhut, untill you reade more how that ye ſhall make this Oyle.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:14357:80"/>
                     <head>To calcine Tinne or Lead.</head>
                     <p>TAke Tinne or Lead and melt it on the fire, and when it is molte ſet it very hot, then take an Iron Scummer and ſtirre it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſo long, till it come to aſhes, then take that aſhes and waſh it ſo long till that the water runneth deare off as yee put it on, then dry it in a calcining Furnace till that it ſmoke no more, then put it into another new pot with a cover, that is unglaſed, and lute it very well, then ſet it in the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cining Furnace againe one
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:14357:80"/>whole day with a good fire, then take it forth and yee ſhall find a Calxe in manner white, but ſomewhat incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to yellow. The Tinne yee ſhall calcine in the ſelfe ſame manner as yee did the Lead, but when yee burne it to aſhes yee muſt giue it great fire, but in calcining it ſhall not need greater fire then it was for thy Lead, and ſo keepe your fire untill it be as white as ſnow, and then it is prepared to make his Oyle as wee will ſhew you hereafter.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:14357:81"/>
                     <head>To Calcine Silver.</head>
                     <p>TAke Silver and diſſolve it in <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> then caſt a peece of Copper into the glaſſe where the water is with the ſilver, and ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies powre theron a good quantity of raine water, and then the ſilver will fall to the bottom in a Calxe: then let it ſtand ſo one night, or as long as ye will, and then powre away the cleere wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and dry the Calx on the fire, then waſh that with warme water ſo long that it have no bitter taſte of the <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> and when ye have ſo done, ye ſhall take common ſalt prepared as I
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:14357:81"/>have ſhewed you before, and lay it in a Cruſible the thickneſſe of a ſtraw, and then lay thereon your Calx of Silver, and cover it with the ſame ſalt againe, then lute your Cruſible with a cover that no ayre may come foorth, then ſet it in a calcining furnace with a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable fire ſixe houres long, then take it forth and put thereon faire water, and let it ſeeth two or three Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Noſters, and then the ſalt will ſeeth away, and the Calx will remaine ſweet, which ye may proove upon the tongue: but if it be not ſweet, waſh it againe till it be ſweet, and then keepe it in a glaſſe, for it is prepared to make his Oyle.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:14357:82"/>
                     <head>To calcine Gold.</head>
                     <p>TAke gold and <hi>Mercury,</hi> and make thereof amal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamie as the Goldſmithes doe uſe to gild their ſilver Plate: the which is made thus.</p>
                     <p>Take twelue parts of <hi>Mercury,</hi> and one part of gold, the which yee ſhall beate into very thin plates, and then cut it in as ſmall peeces as yee can, then take a Cruſible and put therein the <hi>Mercury,</hi> and ſet it on the fire till it beginne to ſmoke, then put thereto the gold and take it from the fire, and ſtirre it together ſo long till that yee may ſee no more gold, then ſet
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:14357:82"/>it on the fire againe, and ſtir it ſo long that the <hi>Mercury</hi> be flowne all away, and then yee ſhall find your gold in the Cruſible like ſand, then take that and put thereto as much prepared ſalt, and grind them together on a ſtone as ſmall as is poſſible, then put it in a glaſſe, and waſh it with warme water ſo long till that yee ſee the Calxe faire and yellow and ſweet upon the tongue, ſo that it taſte nothing of ſalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then it is prepared: and herewith will wee make an end of <hi>Calcination,</hi> and write of <hi>Sublimation.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="138" facs="tcp:14357:83"/>
                     <head>To ſublime Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver.</head>
                     <p>TAke <hi>Mercury</hi> and waſh it with Vineger and ſalt a pretty while, then put thereon very hot water and waſh it therewith, till that the water runne as cleare off as ye will put it on, then dry it with a cloth and grinde it with vineger &amp; ſalt againe, and waſh it with warme water as ye did afore: this grinding and waſhing ye ſhall uſe till that the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> be no more blacke, and that it be as cleare as a glaſſe, then take of that <hi>Mercury</hi> one pound, <hi>Salt</hi> prepared two pound, <hi>Sall Armoniack</hi> ſublimed as I will ſhew
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:14357:83"/>hereafter one pound, grinde theſe ſaltes together with the <hi>Mercury,</hi> ſo long till that the <hi>Mercury</hi> cannot be perceived: then put all the ſubſtance in a ſubliming veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell with his cover, the which hath a hole in the top: as I will ſhew thee hereafter in the next booke, if God permit me life. Then ſet it in a calcining furnace, and give it firſt a ſmall fire till that the moyſture bee flowne out thorow the hole of the cover of the Sublima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, the which yee ſhall know by this meanes: ye ſhall now and then holde a knife over the hole of the inſtrument, and then if the knife be wet there is moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture in the veſſell, but when
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:14357:84"/>yee ſee that the knife is ſtill dry, ſtop the hole with a ſtopple of paper, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the fire a little big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and let it ſtand ſo foure houres long, then encreaſe the fire yet bigger, and let it ſtand foure houres: then make the fire ſo hot that the bottome may be all red, and that continue ſixe houres, but let not your fire ſlake, then let it waxe cold and take that which is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limed, and grind it on a ſtone with two pound of ſalt prepared, and ſublime it againe as yee did afore in all points, then let it waxe cold, and grind it againe with Salt prepared, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime it againe. This grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and ſubliming yee ſhal
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:14357:84"/>uſe untill the <hi>Mercury</hi> bee as cleare as Chriſtall, and as white as Snow and then it is prepared, then keepe it in a glaſſe till that I write more thereof.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To ſublime Sulphure.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt before that yee will ſublime <hi>Sulphur,</hi> ye muſt prepare him thus.</p>
                     <p>Take <hi>Sulphure</hi> vive and grind it to fine powder, then ſearce it finely, then put it in a pan with ſtrong vineger, and ſet it on the fire, and let it ſeeth a whole day and a night, but yee muſt put thereto alwayes more vineger as it conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth avvay, and ſtill yee muſt skum off the skim or filth as faſt as it riſeth, and vvhen it hath ſodden
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:14357:85"/>ſo in Vineger, ye ſhall ſeeth it two daies in the Vrine of young children, and alwayes skum off the froth, and put thereto more Vrine alwaies as it conſumeth. This ſeeth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and skumming ye ſhall continue untill there riſe no more froth, then put it in a glaſſe, and waſh it with warme water till all the ſtinke of the piſſe be gone, and that it remaine as white as any Snow: then dry it wel for it is well purged, then take of that purged <hi>Sulphur</hi> halfe a pound, <hi>Vitriall</hi> calci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned one pound grind theſe very fine together, ſo that the <hi>Sulfure</hi> cannot be ſeene, then put them in a ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming veſſell, and ſet it in the furnace, and give it firſt
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:14357:85"/>a ſmall fire till the moiſture be gone, the which ye ſhall know with a knife as I ſhewed you afore: then ſtop the hole and increaſe the fire a little, and ſo keepe it ſixe houres, then let it waxe cold and take that which is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limed, and grind it vvith freſh <hi>Vitrioll</hi> and ſublime it againe as ye did afore: this ſubliming and grinding vvith freſh <hi>Vitrioll,</hi> ye ſhall uſe till that the <hi>Sulfure</hi> be as vvhite as Snovv, &amp; ſo cleere as a glaſſe, and then it is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limed enough: therefore keepe it in a glaſſe cloſe ſhut vvith Waxe, till that vve vvrite more thereof.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:14357:86"/>
                     <head>To ſublime Sal Armoniacke.</head>
                     <p>TAke <hi>Sal Armoniack</hi> l'i. and as much limall of Iron and grind them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on a ſtone, then put them in a ſubliming veſſell, and ſeeth it in the furnace firſt with a ſmall fire, and then increaſe it ſo that the bottome of the pot may be red hot, and ſo let it ſtand halfe a Summers day, then let it waxe cold and take that which is ſublimed and grinde it on a ſtone, with as much ſalt prepared and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime it againe: This grind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with new ſalt and ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, ye ſhall uſe ſo long till that it bee ſublimed as
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:14357:86"/>white as Snow and then it is prepared: then keepe it to ſublime thy <hi>Mercurie</hi> with.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To ſublime Copper, which is a great ſecret.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt yee muſt calcine it with <hi>Sulphur</hi> thus.</p>
                     <p>Take plates of Copper beaten as thin as is poſsible, and cut them in little peeces as bigge as a peny or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about, then take a cruſible and put therein Brimſtone beaten a finger thicke, then lay thereon a bed of theſe plates and cover them with <hi>Sulphur,</hi> &amp; then lay another bed and cover it with <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur</hi> againe, and this doe till
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:14357:87"/>the Cruſible bee full, then ſet it in the calcining Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace halfe a day long with a good fire, then let it waxe cold and grinde it upon a ſtone, and then put it into <hi>Aqua fortis</hi> &amp; let it diſſolue: and diſtill away the water and make the powder very dry, the which remaineth in the bottome of the glaſſe land grinde it on a ſtone with ſalt prepared: then put it in a ſubliming veſſell, and ſet it in a Furnace, and giue firſt a ſmall fire, and then giue it a very ſtrong fire foure and twenty houres: and then let it waxe cold, and in the veſſell yee ſhall find a greene powder light and ſubtile, but nothing like the Copper, the which yee
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:14357:87"/>had to ſublime. Then keepe that in a glaſſe cloſe ſhut with waxe, for there is no better medicine in the world then this for the Canker, the Wolfe, Fiſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laes, and all ſuch like ſores, for this doth helpe them quickly: and when yee will occupy it in ſuch ſores, yee muſt ſtraw it thereon , and lay upon it a wound plaiſter: of the which I haue written a number in my pearle of Chirurgery, and it ſhall heale them how ſore ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they be.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="148" facs="tcp:14357:88"/>
                     <head>To ſublime Lead and Tinne.</head>
                     <p>THeſe two are ſublimed with leſſe labour then the Copper: nevertheleſſe when ye ſhall ſublime them, goe to worke as thou didſt with Copper, ſaving that ye may not calcine them with <hi>Sulfur,</hi> but as I haue ſhewed you afore. And when it is ſo calcined yee ſhall diſſolue them in this ſtrong water following: and when it is diſſolved diſtill the water away till it remaine dry: then diſſolue it againe, and diſtill the water away a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ſo that it remaine ſcant dry: then take that, and put thereto twiſe ſo
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:14357:88"/>much ſalt prepared and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime them together with a ſtrong fire, and yee ſhall find a white powder ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the top, the which ſerveth to the ſame uſe that the copper ſerveth for: that is in all foule Vlcerations and filthy ſores, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How to make the ſaid Aqua fortis to diſſolue Lead and Tinne.</head>
                     <p>TAke ſalt Peter, <hi>Vitrioll Roman</hi> and <hi>Sal Armoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack,</hi> of each one pound, beate them well together and put them in a glaſſe, the which is very well luted: then ſet on the head with a great receiver, and lute the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:14357:89"/>joynts well that no ayre may come forth, then giue it a very ſmall fire twelue houres long, and then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crcaſe it according to Art: but take good heed that yee bee not raſh with your fire at the firſt, leſt that all the glaſſes fly in peeces: then keepe it to thy uſe, and when yee will diſſolue your Lead, yee muſt take for every pound of Lead, two pound of water, and diſſolue it cold, for otherwiſe it would blow the glaſſe in peeces.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="151" facs="tcp:14357:89"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Sulphure, the which is a great ſecret.</head>
                     <p>THis oyle is made in this manner. Firſt yee ſhall haue a bell of earth, or a head of glaſſe like the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Stils of Tin, the which yee ſhall hang up by a ſtring: then take a plate of Iron of a finger thicke, and two fingers broade, and make it red hot in the fire, then lay it under the bell or head, and caſt thereon Brimſtone, &amp; let it burne, ſo that the fume may go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bell, and this yee ſhall continue, poſſible a whole day, afore that one drop wil fal: but when ye ſee it drop,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:14357:90"/>then continue till yee haue oyle enough, and then haſt thou a great treaſure, the which keepe in a glaſſe, for it will helpe the poxe and all outward ſores and ulce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. And alſo ſtincking and filthy ſores, the which will not bee holpe. It is alſo excellent againſt the Roſe, and againſt the peſtilence, the which yee muſt uſe in this manner. Take water of Sorell, of Roſes, of <hi>Cardus Benedictus</hi> of each <seg rend="greek-xi">
                           <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>
                        </seg>. i. oyle of Sulfer <seg rend="greek-tai-lig">℈</seg>. i. mixe them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and giue it the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent as ſoone as he feeleth himſelfe ſicke, and lay him downe to ſweat one houre, and let him not ſtirre that he may ſweate the better, then dry him well with
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:14357:90"/>warme clothes, and let him reſt two houres, and then if hee haue liſt to eate, let him haue a cullus made of a Hen in this order. Yee ſhall boyle the Henne or chicken ſo long, that the fleſh fall from the bones, then ſtampe the bones and all, and ſtraine it with the ſaid broth, then put thereto a good deale of Sugar, and a little Wine, and let the patient eate it with a very little bread: and then two houres after, yee ſhall giue him the aforeſaid receipt with Oyle, and let him ſweat thereon two houres, as is ſaid afore, and this yee ſhall doe the next day once, and by the Grace of God the Peſtilence ſhall not hurt him. But when yee
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:14357:91"/>will occupy it to the Poxe, or any other filthy ſores, yee ſhall giue it with water of Hops, of Cicorie, of Germander, of eche <seg rend="greek-xi">
                           <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>
                        </seg>. i. water of Fumetorie <seg rend="greek-xi">
                           <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>
                        </seg>. ii. Oyle of Sulphure <seg rend="greek-tai-lig">℈</seg>.i. theſe yee ſhall mixe together, and let the Patient drinke it at ſeven a clock in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and let him ſweat thereon two houres: then dry him with warme clothes, and then at night yee ſhall giue him that por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in manner as yee did before, and let him ſweat thereon other two houres: and this order yee ſhall uſe till that they be whole, the which will be in very ſhort time, ſo that it ſhall ſeeme miraculous, for his ſores
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:14357:91"/>will preſently be healed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were never ſo evill.</p>
                     <p>Againſt the Roſe ye ſhall take the water of Sorell, of Purſelene, and put thereto <seg rend="greek-tai-lig">℈</seg>.i. of oyle of Brimſtone, and let the Patient drinke it, and lye downe to ſweat thereon, and in one day hee ſhall be holpe, although hee had it a long time.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trioll.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt yee muſt haue an earthen pot, the which holdeth about a gallon, and muſt be about a foot, or four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen inches high, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye muſt haue a head of glaſſe, the
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:14357:92"/>which commeth juſt over the pit, then take vitrioll and put it in the pot, and then ſet on the head, with a great receiver, and lute the joynts well, then giue it ſmall fire, as I haue ſhewed you afore in the making of ſtrong water, and when yee ſee that it will drop no more, then encreaſe the fire a little, and ſo keepe it till it drop no more, then take away the receiver, and poure out the water, and ſet it to againe, and lute it faſt, then encreaſe thy fire by little and little, till that the fumes come forth: then keepe it bigger and bigger, ſo that the pot may ſtand as hot as the coales, and ſo keepe it untill that the head
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:14357:92"/>and receiver waxe cleare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, but in any wiſe ſlacke not thy fire: for I haue ſeene fire kept a whole day, after that the water was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, and never a drop fell into the receiver, but at the laſt it came apace, therefore leaue not till it be done. Then keepe this oyle very cloſe in a glaſſe, that the ſpirits fly not away, for when it hath loſt his ſpirits, it is good for nothing, but to corrode and eate away dead fleſh. But when this oyle hath his ſpirits, there is no better medicine in the world, againſt the falling ſickeneſſe and Apoplexia being vſed thus: Take <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua vitae</hi> perfectly rectified, without fleme one pint,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:14357:93"/>Oyle of <hi>Vitrioll</hi> one ſpoone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, mixe them and let the Patient drinke thereof eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry morning one ſpoonefull, and he ſhall bee holpen, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee haue had it ten yeares, and fell every houre: and for Apoplexia yee ſhall giue it in the ſaid order. But if hee cannot drinke it ſo, yee ſhall giue it as yee thinke good, ſo as he haue it in his body, and preſently he ſhall mend, although he had it a long time, and were lame over all his body. It is alſo excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t good againſt all hot fevers in the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, for it helpes them in one day, as I haue proved divers times my ſelfe, and yee ſhall giue it in this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Take bourage water
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:14357:93"/>as much as yee will, and put thereto ſo much of this oyle, till it bee ſowre like veriuice, and thereof let the Patient drinke as much as he will, and then yee ſhall ſee the Patient holpe, and his thirſt ſhall ſlake, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo his heate. This oyle is alſo good againſt all foule &amp; old ſores, &amp; to take away their ſtinke, if yee doe mixe it with water of Egremony, till it bee very ſowre, and then waſh the fore there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. If ye mixe more oyle with the ſaid water, untill it be as ſowre as vineger, it takes away warts if ye waſh them therwith, and cauſeth them to fall out without paine. It helpes all ſcabs if ye waſh them therewith, mixt
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:14357:94"/>with Egremony water as is aforeſaid. If yee mixe it with bourage water, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gloſſe water, and melliſe water, it helps the beating of the heart, which hath continued a long time.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To make water of Mercury, which <hi>Paraſelſus</hi> writeth of in his booke of Chirurgery.</head>
                     <p>TAke Mercurie that is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limed, as I haue ſhewed you afore, and put it in a glaſſe, and ſet it in a furnace, and giue ſuch a temperate fire, as you may hold your hand over it <hi>Paſter noſter</hi> while, and that degree of
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:14357:94"/>fire yee ſhall keepe, the ſpace of ſixe weekes, but looke that yee encreaſe not the fire, nor yet diminiſh it: then take that Mercury and grind it fine, and poure it into a bagge, like unto an Ipocraſſe bagge, and hang it in a moiſt place, and ſet a glaſſe under it, and the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury will turne into water, which keepe well: and when thou wilt occupy that water, thou ſhalt wet a linnen cloath therein, and lay it on ſuch kind of ſores, as will not bee holpe by no other kind of meanes: for it will take away their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rofiues, and cauſe them to heale, although they were never ſo ill. And moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, becauſe that thou ſhalt
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:14357:95"/>know wherefore it ſerveth, yee ſhall note that it is good againſt all Cankers, Fiſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laes, the wolfe, and ſuch like, for it helpeth them al, though they were never ſo evill, as <hi>Paraſelſus</hi> writes in his great Surgery in the chapter of the Canker, and ſuch like.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To make water of ſal Armoniake.</head>
                     <p>TAke <hi>Sal Armoniake</hi> that is ſublimed ſeven times, and grinde it to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, then put it into a glaſſe, that hath a hole in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome on the one ſide, and then ſet that glaſſe in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:14357:95"/>and ſet them in a moiſt ſellar, and then the <hi>Sal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacke</hi> will diſſolue into water, and runne into the neather glaſſe, the which yee ſhall keepe cloſe: in the aforeſaid manner yee may make water of Allum, the which is excellent to dry up all filthy wounds, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The order to fixe all things that are flying.</head>
                     <p>TO fixe any thing, is to be underſtood thus. Ye ſhall ſublime it ſo often, as it will ſublime no more, but it will lie in the fire, ſo as the fire cannot conſume it, and
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:14357:96"/>when ye will fixe any thing, as Sulphur, Quickeſilver, or Arſnicke, or ſuch like, yee ſhall doe it in this order: yee ſhall take Mercurie ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limed, or Sulphur ſublimed, or Arſenicke, or ſuch like, and put it into a ſubliming glaſſe, which I will ſhew you divers Paternes, in the next booke (God willing) and ſet it in a Furnace with a ſmall fire, and then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe it according to Art, the ſpace of a whole day, and then at Evening yee ſhall turne the glaſſe and let it ſublime up into the other end: and this order yee ſhall uſe with ſubliming, from one end unto another, till that it will ſublime no more: the which yee ſhall
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:14357:96"/>proue in this manner. Yee ſhall take a little thereof and lay it on a red hot coale, and look whether it ſmoke or no, for if it ſmoke it is not fixt, but if it ſmoke not it is fixt: but to know the very truth, yee ſhall take thereof and grinde it to powder, and then put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Cruſible, and giue it as great a fire as though yee would melt Copper, and then if yee ſee there com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth no ſmoake from it, it is fixt: but if it ſmoake away, yee ſhall put it into a new ſubliming glaſſe, and ſublime it againe, then keep it to thy uſe, till I write more thereof: for when you haue your ſpirits fixt, yee haue a great treaſure,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:14357:97"/>not to be bought with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and principally of Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phure fixt, for therewith ye may doe what yee liſt, for there can no ſickneſſe come unto mans body, but it may bee holpe therewith. Alſo <hi>Mercury</hi> being fixt, is ſuch an excellent medicine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the poxe, that the like cannot bee found in the world. But yee ſhall note, that it muſt not be occupied alone, but with other things which I will ſhew you in an other place. The Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke and the <hi>Sal Armoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acke</hi> may not bee occcupied in any wiſe inwardly, but onely outwardly, as yee ſhall heare hereafter, and eſpecially of the ſalt of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenicke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="167" facs="tcp:14357:97"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timonie.</head>
                     <p>IF you will make this oyle, yee muſt looke di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to your fire, leſt ye ſpoyle all: then take a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort of glaſſe, and lute it very well, and put therein three pounds of <hi>Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> and three pounds of <hi>Sal gemme</hi> calcined, beaten together, then encreaſe your fire according to Art, three dayes and three nights, and lute thy receiver very well, which muſt bee of the quantity of fiue or ſixe gallons, or more, the greater the better, and then thou ſhalt haue an oyle as red as blood, which is not
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:14357:98"/>to bee ſold or bought for money: for it helpeth the Canker, the Wolfe, <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> and Fiſtulaes, if yee annoynt them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: firſt the dead fleſh will fall out without paine, and then it will heale, how ſore ſoever it bee, although it were forty yeares old.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In ſumma.</hi> It is a moſt excellent oyle againſt all ſores and venemous Vlcers, for if yee annoynt them three times therewith, it helpes them, although they were ſo venemous as they did eate a hand broad in one night, as is divers times ſeene of the Wolfe, and ſuch like ulcerations, that eate ſo, as it ſeemes a dogge had bitten out a great peece.
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:14357:98"/>Theſe and all other ulcera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which will not bee holpe by any meanes, yee ſhall helpe them with this oyle in ſhort ſpace, ſo as ſhall ſeeme marvellous to behold.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>How yee may draw forth Salt out of all mettalles and firſt out of Gold, which is called <hi>Sal ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FIrſt if you will make ſait of Gold, you ſhall take gold filed into powder, and diſſolue it in the afore written ſtrong water, and when it is diſſolved, yee ſhall boyle away the water,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:14357:99"/>till it remaine dry, then thou ſhalt put thereon faire water, and let it ſeeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with three or foure houres long, and then poure it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and put more thereon and let it ſeeth againe, and then poure it off againe: this pouring on and off yee ſhall uſe till the water haue no taſte of the ſtrong wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but is ſweet: and when it is ſo, giue it great fire that it may dry well, then put it in a glaſſe and ſet it in a cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cining Furnace, and there it ſhal calcine a whole moneth long, ſo that it remaine al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes red hot and at one degree of fire, then take and grinde it on a ſtone, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it be as fine as is poſſible: then poure thereon good
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:14357:99"/>diſtilled vineger, and lay a cover over the glaſſe, and let it ſeeth in <hi>Balneo Mariae</hi> a whole day long, putting thereto alwayes freſh vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: then poure off that vineger into a glaſſe and put thereon more, and boyle it a whole day as ye did afore, and this yee ſhall doe three times: then take that vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that yee poured off and diſtill it by <hi>Balneo Mariae</hi> till it remaine dry, and in the bottome yee ſhall find a ſalt as white as ſnow, which yee ſhall take and put thereon more vineger, and ſet it in the <hi>Balneo Mariae</hi> that it may boyle the ſpace of two houres, then let it ſettle a whole day, and then poure off that which is cleare, and
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:14357:100"/>then if there remaine any thing in the bottome it is not enough prepared: then ſhall yee diſſolue it in vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger againe, and diſtill the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger againe as I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you, and yee ſhall find a whiter ſalt in the bottome of the glaſſe, which ye ſhall put in vineger againe, and let that boyle in <hi>Balneo Mariae</hi> two houres, as I haue afore ſhewed you, and then let it ſtand and ſettle, and then poure off the clearer part, and diſtill it in <hi>Bailneo Mariae,</hi> and the ſalt will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the bottome as white as ſnow. But if there remaine any in the other glaſſe yee ſhall not doe as I haue ſhewed you, till it bee all diſſolved.</p>
                     <pb n="173" facs="tcp:14357:100"/>
                     <p>Then diſſolue that ſalt in raine water three or foure times, and looke whether there remaine any ſalt in the bottome undiſſolved, and if there remaine none, it is well prepared, or elſe not, and it is called <hi>Sal philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorum,</hi> or <hi>ſapientiae,</hi> and when it is diſſolved into cleare water, that the ſalt may remaine very dry in the bottome, the which ye ſhall keepe in a glaſſe cloſe there, for it is a mod excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent medicine againſt all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes of the body, for it will leaue nothing in a mans body that ſhall hurt him, but it doth driue it forth by ſweat, and maketh the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient as ſound and whole as ever he was in all his life. It
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:14357:101"/>helpeth all outward ſores, as the Canker, the Wolfe, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulaes, and ſuch like.</p>
                     <p>This being taken inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doth helpe thoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſeaſes moſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull: for it helpeth them in three or foure dayes, and when yee will occupy it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch diſeaſes, yee ſhall uſe it in this manner.</p>
                     <p>Yee ſhall take a Viall full of wine, and put therein two or three graines of that ſalt, for it is ſufficient for any ſicke perſon, for any kind of diſeaſes, then ſtop that Viall and ſet it in warme water, untill the ſalt be diſſolved, then giue the ſicke perſon thereof to drinke warme, and lay him downe to ſweat, for it will
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:14357:101"/>cauſe him to ſweat wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, therefore keepe him from the cold in any wiſe, for that ſweat will bring him to health againe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he were a Leaper, ſo that it come not by nature of his mother, for if it come by kind, there is no helpe that I doe know, yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe this medicine can not hurt, nor yet it cannot helpe him. But other ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, although they were never ſo evill or ſore, it will helpe them. It helps the Peſtilence miraculouſly in one day, and likewiſe the poxe in ſhort time, giving it as is aforeſaid in wine, and lay thereon and ſweat, and
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:14357:102"/>when thou wilt helpe any outward ſore, thou ſhalt lay thereon a wound plaiſter, and let him drinke the ſaid ſalt with wine morning and evening, as is ſaid afore, and in ſhort ſpace they ſhall be holpen,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The order to diſtill vineger to make the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſalts.</head>
                     <p>TAke good ſtrong re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh wine vineger, and diſtill it in a Limbecke of glaſſe, and giue it firſt a ſmall fire till halfe be diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, then take it away, for it is nothing worth to our worke, then taſte it on thy
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:14357:102"/>tongue whether it be ſharpe or no, if it bee not ſharpe, it is not good: if not, keepe that ſmall fire till the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor come forth ſowre: yee ſhall note that the worſt of the vineger di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilleth firſt, then diſtill that which is laſt with a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable fire till it bee almoſt diſtilled, but yee may not diſtill it all quite out, leſt it ſhould ſtinke of the fire, and waxe red, for then will it not ſerue our purpoſe. Moreover yee ſhall note that it may not drop faſter, but that a man may ſay a <hi>Pater noſter</hi> betweene.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="178" facs="tcp:14357:103"/>
                     <head>To draw forth the ſalt of Arſnicke.</head>
                     <p>THe ſalt of Arſenicke is a marvellous ſalt, but it is ſharpe and coroſiue, and the order to make it is thus.</p>
                     <p>Take Arſnicke <seg rend="greek-xi">
                           <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>
                        </seg> i. which is fixed, and diſſolue it in <hi>Aqua fortis</hi> made of ſalt Peter and Allum, and when it is diſſolved put thereon raine water, till it ſincke to the bottome, and when it is ſuncke to the bottome let it ſtand to ſettle, then poure off that part which is clear, and put on more freſh wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and let it ſeeth, and then
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:14357:103"/>let it ſettle and poure off the water againe, and then poure on more: and this order yee ſhall uſe untill the water come off as ſweet as yee put it on, then calcine it ſixe dayes and ſixe nights, then poure thereon diſtilled vineger and ſeeth it in <hi>Balneo Mariae</hi> to diſſolue, and at night let it ſettle and waxe cleare: then poure off that which is cleare and put on more, and let it ſtand a day to diſſolue as I ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and then let it waxe cleare, and then poure off the cleare parts. This yee muſt doe three times as is ſaid of gold, and then dry it very well, and put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on faire raine water till it be diſſolved, and when it is
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:14357:104"/>diſſolved yee ſhall make no more fire under it, but let it waxe cold, and then poure the cleare parts off and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill it in <hi>Balneo Mariae</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it be dry: and then you ſhall find your ſalt in the ground as white as the ſnow: which is moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent againſt the Canker, the Wolfe, and ſuch like as commeth of wounds, &amp;c. Yee ſhall helpe them thus. Take of this ſalt <seg rend="greek-tai-lig">℈</seg>. j. and put thereto <seg rend="greek-xi">
                           <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>
                        </seg>. j. of <hi>Vnguen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum fuſcum,</hi> and therewith dreſſe the ſores, and they will heale in ſhort time, though they were never ſo old: and therefore if thou wilt underſtand wherefore it ſerues: looke in my pearle of Chirurgery, and
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:14357:104"/>alſo in the Chirurgery of <hi>Paraſelſus.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Mettals, and firſt of Lead and Tinne.</head>
                     <p>IF you will make oyle of theſe two Mettalles, yee muſt firſt calcine them, as I haue ſhewed you, and then diſſolue them in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſtrong water, and when they bee diſſolved let them ſtand till it bee as cleare as a glaſſe, then diſtill away the water by a Limbecke till it remaine dry, and when it is dry, put thereon good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled vineger, and ſet it in <hi>Balneo Mariae</hi> to diſſolua a
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:14357:105"/>whole day, and let it boyle, and then let it waxe cold and ſettle, then poure off that part which is cleare and diſtill it in an other glaſſe, and when your mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is dry, put thereon other diſtilled vineger, and let it ſeeth ſo long untill it bee diſſolved, then diſtill away the vineger, and then put on more vineger: this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving and diſtilling yee ſhall uſe ſo long untill the matter remaine in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome like oyle, then put it forth whileſt it is yet warme, for when it is cold it is ſo tough as yee cannot get it from the glaſſe: This oyle ſo made is moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, for it helpes wounds and ſores in very ſhort
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:14357:105"/>time: and moreover, there is no oyle amongſt all the ſecrets of Phiſicke or Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery that heales a wound ſooner then this oyle doth, for it helpes them in foure and twenty houres, ſo as there bee no bones broke or cut, &amp;c. There is an other manner of making of this oyle which is better, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee will not write in this place.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Copper, and of Crocum Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, or Iron.</head>
                     <p>THeſe mettalles yee muſt firſt calcine, and then diſſolue them in ſtrong wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:14357:106"/>then put thereon raine water till the mettall ſincke to the bottome, then put to ſo much raine water till it haue no taſte of the ſtrong water, then dry it well and put thereon diſtilled Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ſet it in <hi>Balneo</hi> to diſſolue, then diſtill away the Vineger till it remaine dry, then put thereon freſh Vineger, and diſtill that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way till that the matter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine dry: and this order yee ſhall uſe till that the matter remaine moiſt in the bottome like oyle. This oyle is of like vertue as the other, and therefore we will write no more thereof in this place.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="185" facs="tcp:14357:106"/>
                     <head>To make Oyle of Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver.</head>
                     <p>IF thou wilt make this oyle, yee muſt haue <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> fixt or elſe it will not ſerue for our uſe: therefore take that which is fixt and put it in ſtrong water, and ſet it in <hi>Balneo</hi> to diſſolue, and ſet thereon a head, and when it is diſſolved let it ſettle, and then poure off that part which is cleare, and diſtill it in <hi>Balneo Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae,</hi> and your <hi>Mercury</hi> will remaine in the bottome, then put thereon raine wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and waſh it ſo long that the water haue no taſte of the ſtrong water, but
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:14357:107"/>remaine as ſweet as yee put it on: then put thereon diſtilled vineger, and ſet it in <hi>Balneo Mariae</hi> a whole day till it be diſſolved, then diſtill the vineger away, and put thereon freſh, and ſet it in <hi>Balneo Mariae</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to diſſolue, and then diſtill it away againe: and this order yee ſhall uſe till that it remaine like an oyle in the bottome, then take it forth and keepe it in a glaſſe cloſe ſhut, leſt it ſhould looſe his ſtrength. This oyle is of as great operation in freſh wounds as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aforeſaid are: it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other againſt the Poxe to be vſed outwardly, for it helpeth all ſores that come of the Poxe, if yee
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:14357:107"/>annoynt the ſores there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with and in the foreſaid manner: Yee may make oyles of all Mettals, but they are not to be taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and therefore I wil ſhew thee another order how you ſhall make oyles of all the Metals to uſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To make Oyle of Gold, the which is diſtilled through the helme, and it is to be vſed both inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</head>
                     <p>IF thou wilt make oyle of gold, yee ſhall take his ſalt of the which we haue
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:14357:108"/>made mention afore, and put it into a glaſſe with a long neck, and mixe the glaſſe faſt with hermes-ſel, that is with a paire of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tongs as I will ſhew you hereafter: then yee ſhall ſet the ſaid glaſſe in a calcining Furnace, with a fire ſo temperate as though it ſtood in the ſun, and there yee ſhall let it ſtand eight dayes, and then increaſe the fire other 8. dayes, till that ye ſee it begin to waxe yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and then keepe thy fire in that heate till that thou ſeeſt thy glaſſe all yellow, and then increaſe thy fire a little till that ye ſee it waxe a browner yellow: and when yee ſee that: yee ſhall keepe it in that heate eight
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:14357:108"/>dayes, and then if yee ſee it change no colour, increaſe your fire a little more eight dayes, and then yee ſhall ſee it waxe red, and when it is indifferent red, yee ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe your fire againe eight dayes, till that yee ſee it a brown red, then ye may giue it a greater fire, for it is fixt, &amp; no fire can conſume it: and when ye haue kept it 8 daies in ſuch a great heate, ye ſhall let it waxe cold, and if yee will make this oyle, yee ſhall grind it in fine pouder, &amp; put it into a ſtone pot, and put theron diſtilled vineger, &amp; ſet it in <hi>Balneo Mariae</hi> to diſſolue 4. dayes long, then let it ſettle &amp; poure off the cleare parts, and put theron more vineger &amp; ſtop the pot
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:14357:109"/>very cloſe, and ſet it againe other foure dayes in <hi>Balneo Mariae</hi> to diſſolue, and every day yee ſhall ſtirre it two or three times with a ſtick, then let it waxe cold and ſettle, and poure off the cleare parts, and then put thereon freſh vineger, and ſet it to diſſolue againe, and let it ſtand and ſettle untill the fifth day in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then let it waxe cold and ſettle, and then poure off the cleare parts, and if there remaine any thing in the pots bottome, caſt it out, for it is not profitable for our worke, then waſh the pot very cleane, and put therein the ſaid Vineger, that yee boyled afore, and diſtill it <hi>per Balneo Mariae</hi>
                        <pb n="191" facs="tcp:14357:109"/>untill it be dry, and yee ſhall find the powder fairer then it was afore, and then put thereon freſh Vineger, and ſet it to diſſolue in <hi>Balneo Mariae,</hi> as is ſaid afore. And when it hath ſtood foure dayes, yee ſhall poure it cleare off, and looke if there remaine any feces or powder in the bottome, and if there be any you ſhall poure it out, and make the pot cleane, and put therein the ſaid Vineger which yee poured off, and diſtill it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <hi>per Balneo Mariae,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that it remaine dry: then put thereon freſh Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger, and diſſolue it as I haue ſhewed you, and then poure off the Vineger and diſtill it againe, and this yee
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:14357:110"/>ſhall uſe, untill you find no more ſand in the bottome. But that it is all diſſolved, and then it is prepared to make his oyle of, then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill that laſt vineger away <hi>per Balneo Mariae,</hi> untill that it be very dry, then put it into a glaſſe with a head and a great receiver, the which yee muſt lute together ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well that no aire may come forth, then giue it ſmall fire foure houres long, and then encreaſe it a little ſtronger, and ſo keepe it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foure houres, and then yee ſhall ſee certaine yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low fumes riſe up into the head, then keepe thy fire in that degree, untill that thou ſeeſt the head waxe red, then increaſe your fire a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:14357:110"/>untill that the head be as red as blood, then keepe thy fire in that ſtate, untill thou ſeeſt the colour begin to ſlake. Then make thy fire greater, untill that the bottome of the veſſell bee red, and then keepe it in that ſtay one houre, and then the head will ſeeme to bee full of Snow. Then make the fire as great as thou canſt, untill the head waxe cleare againe as it was at the firſt. Then let it waxe cold, and thou ſhalt find an oyle in the receiver, the which is not to bee bought for any money: For becauſe it helpeth all diſeaſes in mans body, both inwardly and outwardly: although they bee never ſo evill, as
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:14357:111"/>the Peſtilence, the Poxe, the Wolfe, the Canker, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions, the Dropſie, and the Leaper, if ſo bee that it came not by nature of the father and mother. And the order to take it is thus: Yee ſhall take a pot of wine and put therein <seg rend="greek-tai-lig">℈</seg>.j. of this oyle, and giue the ſicke thereof to drinke in the morning, and let him lie in his bed and ſleepe, and then thou ſhalt ſee his wonders. And if ſo bee that the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent be full of evill humors, and that hee ſhall need pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, it will cauſe nature to caſt forth either by ſweat, or vrine, or by vomite, or downeward, as long as the Patient ſhall haue need, and then ſtraight wayes amend
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:14357:111"/>and waxe ſtronger, then if he had eate a whole Capon: and then if the Patient doe purge no more by any of the ſaid meanes aforeſaid, yee ſhall giue it him but three dayes. For if he doe purge more then one day, it is a token that hee is full of corruption, as of the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pry, and the Poxe, for thoſe are ſo full of corruption, ſo that hee cannot bee holpe in one day by nature. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yee ſhall giue it more then three dayes, that is thus to bee underſtood, yee ſhall giue it him ſo long that nature purgeth no more, and that yee may ſee that the Patient waxeth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrong, for this medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine worketh with the
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:14357:112"/>helpe of nature a long tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> after, and therefore this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine is pretious, and of too quicke operation to giue to any ſicke perſon, where no need is. But as for the wolfe and the Canker, and ſuch like outward ſores, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſhall underſtand, that there is neede of no other helpe then the aforeſaid drinke as is ſaid afore: and yee ſhall lay upon the ſore a coole Leafe or Lint, and you ſhall fee great aboun-dance of foule and rotter blood and ſuch like come forth: The which is ſcant to bee beleeved, and then thoſe holes or ſores will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnat, and heale of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues without fault.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:14357:112"/>
            <list>
               <head>THE TABLE OF THE FIRST Booke of the Secrets of <hi>Phyſicke</hi> and <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy,</hi> wherein is ſhewed how.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> TO make Oyle of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke. <hi>fol. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> To make Oyle of Mirra. <hi>fol. 5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> To make oyle of Storax Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quida. <hi>fol. 8.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:14357:113"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> To make oyle of Storax Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamite. <hi>fol. 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> To make oyle of Benjamin, <hi>fol. 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> To make oyle of Galbanum, <hi>fol. 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> To make oyle of Sagapenum, <hi>fol. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> To make oyle of Opoponax, <hi>fol. 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> To make oyle of Euphorbium, <hi>fol. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> To make oyle of Ambre or Succinum, <hi>fol. 18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> To make oyle of Amonia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,
<pb facs="tcp:14357:113"/>
                  <hi>fol. 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> To make oyle of Sorcocolla. <hi>fol. 22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> To make oyle of Caſtoreum <hi>fol. 23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> To make oyle of Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe. <hi>fol. 25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> To make oyle of Turpentine, <hi>fol. 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi> To make oyle of Waxe, <hi>fol. 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi> To make Quinteſſence of Honey, <hi>fol. 32.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18.</hi> To make oyle of Lignum Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae or Guai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um. <hi>fol. 38</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:14357:114"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>19.</hi> To make Oyle of Butter, <hi>fol. 42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20.</hi> To make Oyle of Egges. <hi>fol. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21.</hi> To make Oyle of Sinamon. <hi>fol. 44.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22.</hi> To make Oyle of Cloves. <hi>fol. 48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>23.</hi> To make Oyle of Nutmegs. <hi>fol. 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>24.</hi> To make Oyle of Mace. <hi>fol. 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>25.</hi> To make oyle of Pepper. <hi>fol. 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>26.</hi> To make Oyle of Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron.
<pb facs="tcp:14357:114"/>
                  <hi>fol. 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>27.</hi> To make Oyle of Anniſeed, <hi>fol. 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>28.</hi> To make Oyle of Fennell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed. <hi>fol. 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>29.</hi> To make Oyle of Cummin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed. <hi>fol. 60</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>30.</hi> To make Oyle of Carraway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed. <hi>fol. 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>31.</hi> To make Oyle of Dill ſeed. <hi>fol. 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>32.</hi> To make Oyle of Parcelie ſeed, <hi>fol. 64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>33.</hi> To make Oyle of Rue or Hearbgrace. <hi>fol. 65</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:14357:115"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>34.</hi> To make oyle of Ivy. <hi>fol. 68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>35.</hi> To make oyle of Roſemary flowers. <hi>fol. 72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>36.</hi> To make oyle of Wild Time. <hi>fol. 74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>37.</hi> To make oyle of ſweet Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerom. <hi>fol. 78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>38.</hi> To make oyle of Sage. <hi>fol. 80.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>39.</hi> To make oyle of Peneriall, <hi>fol. 81.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>40.</hi> To make oyle of Mint. <hi>fol. 84.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>41.</hi> To make oyle of Hyſſop, <hi>fol. 86</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:14357:115"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>42.</hi> To make oyle of Radiſh ſeed. <hi>fol. 87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>43.</hi> To make oyle of Muſtard ſeed. <hi>fol. 88</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>44.</hi> To make Oyle of Colewort ſeed. <hi>fol. 89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>45.</hi> To make oyle of Linſeed. <hi>fol. 90</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>46.</hi> To make oyle of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> wort or ſeed. <hi>fol. 91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>47.</hi> To make oyle of Quinces ſeed. <hi>fol. 92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>48.</hi> To make oyle of Acornes. <hi>fol. 93</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>49.</hi> To make oyle of Tartare by
<pb facs="tcp:14357:116"/>diſtillation. <hi>fol. 94</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>50.</hi> Another way to make Oyle of Tartare. <hi>fol. 95</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>51.</hi> To make Oyle of Harts-Horne. <hi>fol. 97</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>52.</hi> To distill Oyle of Mans Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements. <hi>fol. 98</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>53.</hi> To make Oyle of the skull of a man. <hi>fol. 98</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:14357:116"/>
            <list>
               <head>The Table of the ſecond Booke, ſhewing</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> The Names of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls, Simples, or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines ſpoken of therein. <hi>fol. 117</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The names of the Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>fol. 120</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> How to prepare Crocum
<pb facs="tcp:14357:117"/>Martis, and ſuch like as are prepared through cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cination. <hi>fol. 122</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> To prepare Alumes and Salts. <hi>fol. 125</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Toprepare Alume. <hi>fol. 126</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> To calcine Vitrioll. <hi>fol. 127</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> To calcine Quicksilver. <hi>fol. 129</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> To calcine Tartare. <hi>fol. 131</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> To calcine Tinne or Lead. <hi>fol. 132</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:14357:117"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> To calcine Silver, <hi>fol. 134</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> To calcine Gold. <hi>fol. 136</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> To ſublime Quicksilver. <hi>fol. 138</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> To ſublime Sulphur <hi>fol. 141</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> To ſublime Sal Armoniacke. <hi>fol. 144</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> To ſublime Copper, which is a great ſecret. <hi>fol. 145</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi> To ſublime Lead and Tinne. <hi>fol. 148</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:14357:118"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi> How to make Aqua Fortis to diſſolue Lead and Tin <hi>fol. 149</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18.</hi> To make Oyle of Sulphure, the which is a great ſecret. <hi>fol. 151</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19</hi> To make Oyle of Vitrioll. <hi>fol. 155</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20.</hi> To make water of Mercury, which <hi>Paraſelſus</hi> writeth of in his booke of Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery. <hi>fol. 160</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21.</hi> To make water of Sal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacke. <hi>fol. 162</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22.</hi> The order to fixe all things that are flying. <hi>fol. 163</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:14357:118"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>23.</hi> To make oyle of Antimony. <hi>fol. 167</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>34.</hi> How you may draw forth Salts out of all metalles, and firſt out of Gold, which is called <hi>Sal Sapientium. fol. 169.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>35.</hi> The order to diſtill Vineger to make the aforeſaid Salts. <hi>fol. 176.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>36.</hi> To draw forth the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of Arſnicke. <hi>fol<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>37.</hi> To make Oyle of Mettals, and firſt of Lead and Tinne. <hi>fol. 181.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>38.</hi> To make Oyle of Copper,
<pb facs="tcp:14357:119"/>and of Crocum Martis, or Iron. <hi>fol. 183.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>29.</hi> To make Oyle of Quicksil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. <hi>fol. 185.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>30.</hi> To make Oyle of Gold, the which is diſtilled through the belme, and is to bee vſed both inwardly and outwardly <hi>fol. 187.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:14357:119"/>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by. <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>William Lugger,</hi> and are to bee ſold at the Poſterne Gate at Tower Hill. 1633.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
